[Music]
Hey.
Heat. Heat.
[Music]
Hello everybody and welcome to the
weekly geopolitics episode of the Ask
Abija show. I hope everyone is doing
great. We're going to take a lot of
geopolitics questions today as many as
possible. But before we start that, let
us see who all is there on the live
stream. Who all is present? I can see
chat. DSP Vish Pala, Mystic SK,
Ashtavakra, Adant Pi, Alvin Rodriguez,
Animals for Laugh from Mumbai, Random
Skull, Rakshit, Mishra, Rayan, Sedharta
Singh, Aayush Singh, HB, Soldier Boy,
Wayne, Bruce Wayne, ultimate power,
freedom from outcome from Canada. Good
morning sir. Um, satellite Abu Singh,
Shiv Brody, Anerud, the knowledge priest
from Kpur. Hello soldier boy. I am
artistic. Vinit savant geopolitical way
from Indoor. Ainina critical thinker.
Basar Kayatwal from Moscow. Well good
evening to you sir. Ultimate power
critical thinker Shashank Koshik from
Nida. Good to have you sir. Hyphen 2k
Jashri Krishna. Vladimir Putin is also
here with us. Beneath Prajakta Gurpad
good evening. Aayush Singh 439 from
Twitch. Good evening. Shuban Badwaj
Shakar Roy Aush Singh Ara Prabhab Banerj
Shaker Roy Deepika Suraj S NS Ara Praan
once again Sujit Shanaga Binit Priyanka
Jabalia Namaste Shaker Roy event
countdown Sumuk bupal bupalam
um Samak space Bhav Gowami Sumit Agaral
from Rajasthan hello Shashank Koshit
once again Napoleon Shing Singh Shikawat
Jay Mahakal
Critical Rayan Tanesh Pandi Ankita
Bushan Tik G. Okay, whatever that is.
Shashank Koshik Alob Dave Jaganat from
Odisha. Uh Briesh Samyak space Ainta
Anand
Kumoas says Binit.
All right. Ryan Surja Surjakhan from
West Bengal. Good to have you regular
viewer sir. Good to have you sir. Netzen
uh Bandekar Bhoji, Nimish Gupta, Hunter
Kenway, good evening Amish Amish, hello
Animeish, hello Bandekar Bhoji once
again. Light is here. Suas Chandra,
Anime Rud, hello Latangi Suresh from
Tiri Tamil Ladu, the birthplace of Zoho.
Good to have you, sir. Good to have you.
Uh Dilling Pigu says, "Zubinar." All
right. Um Okay. So, all right. All
right. Let's So, let's get let's get
going with the questions. Okay, Rahul
Lakman is here. Ratang Suresh is here.
Aid Pandandy, Amber, Wamshi Kalen and
everyone else. Ajinkulkarnney.
Okay, so Anish is watching with your mom
with with his mom. Well, namaste to mom
and to you as well. So, let's take some
questions. We already have a bunch of
questions lined up. So, let's go. Rishi
says, "Greetings from Moscow." Well,
greetings to you, sir. How different
would Russia and its geography have been
today if Mr. Putin did not take charge?
Well, the geography would have remained
the same, but uh Russia may not have
been a sovereign nation today possibly.
See, uh before Mr. Putin, we had Mr.
Yelson who was leading Russia and Mr.
Yelson did his best to destroy Russia's
economy and to a large extent Russia's
peripheral sovereignty. For example, he
was instrumental in Russia losing the
first Chchin war and Cheschna became a
de facto sovereign nation because of
that.
and he handed over the entire Russian
industry to various uh oligarchs
who then proceeded to destroy Russia's
economy and industry industrial base. So
Mr. Putin or Mr. Yelin presided over the
further destruction of Russia's economy.
Mr. Gorbachov started the process from
1985 onwards and all the way until 1991.
Then Mr. Yelson comes to power and he
proceeds to essentially parcel off the
Russian economy piece by piece and give
it to various private players and you
had the the the introduction of American
elements as well to Russia at this point
in time and Russia's economy went into
the gutter essentially during Mr.
Yelson's time. So if Mr. Putin had not
come to power and somebody else similar
to Mr. would have come to power then
Russia would not be a nation that would
be well you know it would it would not
be a very relevant nation today
uh its geography possibly may may also
have changed yeah maybe some regions
would have broken off further by this
time it's possible so one can only
speculate about that but Mr. Putin
arrested that that decline and he
brought Russia back to the position of
the second most powerful nation in the
world which it is today. All right.
Okay. Interesting question. Critical
thinker says how important is
geopolitics for scientists and
engineers? Well, it doesn't have
immediate importance for scientists and
engineers unless you're working in an
applied field. For example, if you are a
missile developer, if you are u this is
all engineering I'm talking about. If
you are into developing missiles or
developing hypersonic glide vehicles or
jet engines so fighter fighter aircraft
or or UCAVs or drones whatever in that
case it's very re relevant because the
geopolitical demands are going to
determine uh what you're going to be
working on essentially right so in that
case it's very relevant even when it
comes to for example if you are into AI
or semiconductors or something
geopolitics is going to drive the demand
uh for whatever it is that you're
So it's uh significantly important when
it comes to more pure sciences. It's
still important but it's not critically
important. It's not something that will
urgently um you know change what you're
going to work on. Uh so that's how it
is. The the the engineering field is
going to be more uh affected by
geopolitics.
Rishi Jooshi says how did the French
outsmart the Gha Raj if no other EU
vasals could the deep state their status
as quasi sovereign state at least were
allowed to not become a complete vasal
in terms of technology how did they do
this well first of all the most
important thing they did was that they
developed their own independent nuclear
deterrent completely independent of any
other nation let's compare France with
the UK okay so the UK as a nuclear
deterrent on paper. They tested nuclear
weapons in the 20th century with
American help by the way. Okay, the
Americans helped them in the process of
developing nuclear weapons. So they they
developed nuclear weapons but then they
did not develop the means to deliver the
packages wherever they would want to
deliver them. They had a good space
program, a rocket program, high quality
rocket program. They had these uh
hydrogen peroxide based rockets which
would essentially give off steam and if
you if you see the old videos of the uh
British rockets you will see that they
would rise up in the air there would be
no visible exhaust nothing because of
the hydrogen peroxide which was used as
the uh as the fuel as one of the
components of the fuel. It's a highly
reactive thing you know that's a whole
different thing. The British had this,
they had a highquality rocket program.
They completely shelved that, dismantled
that and they said we will rely on the
Americans for uh for missiles and and so
on. So today the British don't have a
missile program, rocket program,
whatever. And their nuclear warheads are
mated to American missiles. I think it's
trident missiles, American Trident
missiles. In the 20th century, it was
American polarist missiles that were
used uh for the British nuclear
deterrent. So the British have nuclear
submarines
and in these submarines you have
American trident missiles on which you
have possibly if it's mated ready to go
in that case you will have uh the
British nuclear warheads.
But if you're employing American
missiles to deliver this, it's highly
likely that the big red button will be
sitting in Washington DC, not in London.
So the British don't really have their
own independent nuclear deterrent. They
are an extension of the American nuclear
deterrent. The French have an
independent nuclear deterrent. They have
their own nuclear submarines and their
own missiles, ICBMs or whatever it is
and their own nuclear warheads entirely
independent of the US. No other NATO
nation, no other US ally or vasal has
these capabilities. They also have their
own aircraft carrier and all that. They
have their own jet engines which they
manufacture themselves. They have their
own fighter jets. They have everything
of their own. They don't depend on the
US or other nations that much or very
very less on other nations for their
national defense. So that gives them an
advantage that no other US vasal has.
But the French are still part of NATO
which means that their military from
time to time comes under the command of
a foreign a non-French general right at
least some part of the military from
time to time will come under the command
of someone who is not French. So that is
a problem and they are also part of the
EU which means they don't have
territorial sovereignty, legis or
legislative so sovereignty or economic
sovereignty. That's why France has a
quasi independent foreign policy far
better than what you have in the UK or
any other Brit any other NATO or EU
nation. So that's what the French have
done. So that's why I say that they have
a quasi independent foreign policy.
Rishi Jooshi says some say that current
demo re-engineer demographic
re-engineering of Europe elements like
the painter seile etc movement are
rising. Why did Germans think that they
were wronged somehow and this uprising
sort of led to World War II? Oh, that's
a whole long story I can't answer in in
like a few minutes here. See, it all
goes back if you if you want me to
compress the history. Uh in 1870 there
was no such thing as Germany. Okay,
remember that there was Prussia and
there were other you know principalities
and so on and then there was around this
time a FrancoRussian war. It was Prussia
against France.
Prussia was Yeah. Well, okay, we'll not
go into older history than that. But I I
took this question related to this
yesterday uh in yesterday's history
session. So in 1871 the the Prussians
prevailed over the French and this led
to the creation of of a nation called
Germany for the first time Deutschand.
It was the brainchild of the the iron
chancellor
um Otoon Bismar. So from 1871 all the
way to 1914 or whatever. Yeah, 14 there
was a period of cold war in Europe and
everyone was waiting for a chance to set
things right. Everyone was waiting,
everyone was developing their military
capabilities. From 1871 all the way to
1914. In 1914, there was this perfect
storm and this war breaks out and
everyone thought in October 1914 that we
will be home by Christmas.
But it did did not work out that way and
the war went on. The first world war,
the first European tribal war went on
until what? 1918, 1919, whichever year
it was. Okay. And it ends with a
humiliation of Germany. Horrific
humiliation of Germany. And that led to
the conditions that
that caused the resumption of the
conflict essentially, which they called
World War II, which is phase two of the
European tribal war. So that's how it
happened because of Germany's
humiliation because of the humiliation
humiliating terms that were imposed upon
Germany during the treaty of the uh
which was where Germany surrendered
right uh so that's the compressed
history of what happened now the details
you can write entire books I have books
here big books multiple books so you
know see if you are really interested
read those books read books about the
world about what caused the world wars
So essentially you would remember that
World War I and World War II are the are
essentially the continuation of a single
conflict. There was a pause in between
between 1918 to 1937 383 39 around that
time right and then it resumes.
An says you are allegedly the best
allegedly. Of course allegedly is very
important sir.
All right. All right. Thank you. uh
godliness says war is necessary to
protect territorial sovereignty but at
the same time romanticism of war is
dangerous. Can you give a comprehensive
brief of how destructive a war can be
for a country like India? A war can be
super destructive for any country. Look
at what happened to Japan.
Two nuclear tests on the citizens of
Japan. Hiroshima Nagasaki. Japan was was
devastated. That's one example. What
happened to Germany? Good God. What
happened to Germany? By by the end of
the second world war, Germany was
flattened.
Millions of Germans were dead.
Millions of Germans were well in the
aftermath of the second world war
genocided. Okay, that that that story is
not supposed to be told. Apparently they
were genocided at the hands of whom? The
allies and well apparently the Russians.
The Russians had good cause to be very
very upset with the the Germans. No
question about it. Right. Uh but you
know it and and what's the what's the
long-term consequences of this for
Germany and Japan? Germany is still
under
US occupation today. You may not realize
it all of you. Okay. The US has a
permanent military presence in Germany
dating back to 1945. The German
constitution was written with the help
of with the help of the US. Let's say,
okay, let's put it uh diplomatically. It
was written with the with the with with
the help of the US. When it comes to
Japan, there is no help of the US. You
can't be that diplomatic. The
Japanese constitution was written by the
Americans in 1945. Until today, not not
a single word has been changed, right?
Japan isn't sovereign. More than 130
permanent US military bases on Japanese
soil. And Japan did take off
economically as long as they were
allowed to. And then their economy was
devastated. Today, Japan has become a
middle- inome nation. It was one of the
highest income nations in the 1980s and
1990s. Today it's on the verge of
becoming a middling nation.
So
the consequences are frightening but
they sometimes take a long time to be
seen. Sometimes they happen overnight.
Look at Iraq.
You had two oil wars. They called them
Gulf Wars. 1991 and 2003. Iraq was
flattened. Millions of people were
killed in those air strikes and
bombardments.
Iraq doesn't exist as a sovereign nation
today. It it is irrelevant today.
It it had a high quality of life, high
high quality of of administration and
everything. Everything is gone. What
what do the people of Iraq have to look
forward to today? So war is devastating.
Devastating. And if you look at other
wars, for example, the settler
colonization wars in the Americas in the
1500s, well, it caused the death of
close to 100 million Native Americans
and they've lost everything. They've
lost their lands. They've lost their
culture. They've lost everything.
Everything they have which was theirs.
Entire continents stolen from them. Um
look at the consequences of war for
India and so on. So yeah, you can go on
for forever about this. Retwick says
three three questions. Why is Kim
Sunsung considered the eternal leader
which is above the supreme leader of
North Korea even if he died 30 years
back. Second, can I India ally with
North Korea to counter the US? Third,
why did Kib Ilssung close off Korea from
the rest of the world? Let's take
question number two first. Can an
elephant ally with an ant
to take on a super
dragon? Not a dragon. The Chinese are
the dragons. Super eagle. So the
elephant is this big, eagle is that big
and ant is this big. What is the point
of the elephant allying or the tiger
let's say India is the tiger. If the
tiger allies with the ant, how will it
offset the might of the great eagle?
How? Makes no sense whatsoever. Okay,
makes no sense whatsoever. And secondly,
North Korea will not align with India
because it is a Chinese asset.
Why is Kimsung considered the eternal
leader? because that gives legitimacy to
the rule of the current Mr. Kim,
Kim Ilsung, Kim Jong-il,
Kim Jong-un. Kim Jong-un, the current
leader, is the third leader in the
dynasty. The dynasty was founded by Kim
Ilsung.
So to legitimize your authority, it
makes a lot of sense to to elevate the
founder of the dynasty to godly to godly
status. Read the Bhagastan inscription.
You may not know what the Bhagastan
inscription is because it is now called
the Behon inscription. It was uh created
by by the emperor of the Akminate
dynasty Daravos also known as Darios.
So he writes in in the inscription which
was written about 2 and a half thousand
years ago roughly. He writes about the
fact that he is a king and he's a
legitimate king because he has a whole
lineage of kings above him who all were
as his ancestors. It legitimizes his
rule. And when Kurush the one of the
Persian uh emperors of the same dynasty
when Kurush defeated Nabuku Kudrachar
Nabuk Nazar he created an inscription in
which he said that you know me Kurush I
am the son of kings who are sons of
kings. I am a legitimate king and this
Nabuku Kudrachar he was a nobody. He had
no royal lineage. So all this matters.
Your lineage matters. If you belong to
an ancient lineage of kings,
trust me, it matters. If you are in if
you are in a position of power, okay?
Because genetics matter. When people
realize that implicitly or explicitly,
people realize that if you come from a
great lineage and you're in a position
of power, it means that you have the
genes, the the blood. It is in your
blood that you that you know how to
rule. You're fit to rule. So that's why
it is important for Kim Jong-un to
elevate his grandfather Kimmel Sun as
the eternal leader that I simply am
carrying his work forward. I am simply
acting on behalf of my godly celestial
deceased grandfather. I am simply his
agent. Okay. I am doing the work but I
he is doing the work through me. That's
what you say. That gives you more
authority, more legitimacy. This is a
psychological thing
and we in India don't have the system of
dynasties and lineages that's why we
don't realize it understand it anymore
but it was also the case in India. So
Ashok one of our great emperors well I'm
sure he also extolled his grandfather
Chandra Gupta Moria right he would have
done that and uh and so on kaneska would
have extolled his lineage which he does
uh raatak inscription which is now in
Afghanistan Gandhar but it was then part
of bharat so kaneshka has an inscription
in in in
raatak it's a village in Afghanistan
today in which he talks about It's
similar to the Bhagastthana inscription
in which he says that I am an I am I am
a descendant of kings and my my lineage
is this my father was this guy and my
his father was this and his father was
that. So it establishes his kingly
lineage. It says that I am fit to rule
because I come from a lineage of kings
and so on. Why did Kim Ilsung close off
Korea from the rest of the world?
Because you have to understand the
context of the time of the times. It was
Kiml Sunsung became the leader in the
aftermath of the Korean war and the
Korean war never ended technically.
So North Korea just south of North Korea
you have US occupied territory and the
war hasn't ended right and uh the whole
of the might of the US and its allies is
arrayed against you and on the side of
North Korea you have China and the USSR.
So it made sense for them to close
everything off from the rest of the
world and you know not allow any foreign
influence in the country because that
would lead to espionage and whatnot. And
they were very paranoid about this maybe
rightfully so. And and the communist
system is always kind of a closed
system. If you look at the Chinese how
they you know conducted business until
the late 1970s they were also closed off
until Nixon and Kissinger hopped on
hopped over to Beijing and then China
slowly opened up slowly very gradually
very very cautiously and the USSR never
opened up. So the system the communist
system was such that it was a closed
system. So yeah made sense for them to
do that. Okay. Vishal says what's the
reason behind daily drone incursions in
the EU? Well, maybe the drones are very
fond of the EU. You know, EU is very
pretty, very pretty nations and very
interesting territory and terrain, very
interesting military logistics and
capabilities. So, the drones wish to
just, you know, do some sightseeing.
Maybe it's a message that the Russians
are sending to the EU. I mean, recently
some airports were were shut down
because drones were flying over the
airports, right? Uh, one of the Nordic
countries, I don't remember which one.
So you had that maybe these were Russian
drones. Maybe these are NATO drones that
are keeping an eye on things. We don't
quite know. Uh so it's see look these
are obviously not UFOs. These are not
alien craft. It's military drones or
surveillance drones of some kind. So it
could either be NATO or Russian drones,
one of the two. So if they're
complaining that drones are in, you
know, intruding into our territory,
they're essentially implying that these
are Russian drones that are u you know
violating the the airspace of the EU
nations. So if the Russians are behind
this, maybe it's a message that's being
sent to the EU and to NATO that you know
we are capable of a lot more than what
we are showing right now. Be careful and
yeah it's a warning essentially possibly
a threat possibly just a friendly
message and maybe it also has the effect
of you know the drones may be doing some
espionage activities some reconnaissance
activities data collection activities
and so on. So that could be the reason
reason behind this.
Ruby says chances of UNFC seat for India
and its geopolitical significance.
Chances big fat zero. Okay. Geopolitic
sign significance nothing. I request my
dear Indians please stop hankering after
these status symbols.
These mean nothing. We will never get a
UN general security council you know
permanency. Never. As long as the US UN
remains in the current shape and form,
India will never get it. Stop begging
for this thing. What India needs to do
is India needs to become so powerful in
its own right that the UN Security
Council permanent membership becomes
completely irrelevant. That's what India
needs to do. The chances are a big fat
zero. Please stop hankering after these
status symbols. We need to stop
hankering after status. We need to start
going after actual hard power.
Abhishek says please history super chat
episode. I'm sure I can do that. The
thing in history super chat I'll tell
you what I don't know the history of the
entire world. If you ask me the history
of let's say Telangana I won't know a
thing about it. Then if I if you ask me
the history of Dr. Ambedkar for example
I don't know a thing about that. If you
ask me the history of I don't know
somebody else there's a lot of history
that I have not read and I can't answer
that geopolitics I can answer
essentially anything
history there are some aspects of
history that I am I'm really good at but
some aspects of history that I've not
looked into I' not not had the time to
look into so if I do a super chat
episode I'm going to get a lot of
questions about stuff that I am not
really an expert on and it would not be
a good idea for me to try and answer
that because that's wrong. Right? So
that's essentially why I don't do these
super chat episodes in history. I simply
pick and choose questions
that interest me and that's how I have
gone about my business thus far but I
will possibly look into this. All right.
So thank you for the suggestion. Ashu
tosh says implications of military
buildup on circ.
Let them do let them do. Okay. What is
circreek? First of all let's see. Okay.
Let's let's uh let's take a look at what
is Sir Creek. It's in Kachra. We all
know Katch the western most part of
Gujarat, right? So here we have let's go
let's zoom in right there. So this
region here is the sir creek and the
Pakistanis have always wanted to take
bites out of you know Katch especially
these little peninsula like fjord like
places over here. They would like to
take some bites out of it and apparently
this is a disputed region for some for
some reason. I'm not sure what the
reason is. So it looks like I mean I'm
sure if you look at the satellite images
right now we will not get the latest
images but apparently there is some kind
of Pakistani military buildup over here.
Let them do it. If they try anything
funny they will
they will pray they will pay a heavy
price for it. So there are no
implications. I'm least concerned about
this so-called buildup of the Pakistani
military in the circreek region. You
want to try something funny? Try it.
Please go ahead. You want to restart
operation zindur? Let's go. Let's play
game on sir. That's all.
Okay. Napoleon Singh Shakawad says, "How
would China be today if Chang Kaiishek
would have won?" Well, that's a
completely hypothetical question. I
would I have it would possibly be
very similar. Perhaps
Chang Kaishek was a dictator. Yes.
And he would have run China very similar
to what Maadong did. Possibly he would
have been friendlier with the west and
less friendly with the Russians which
could have caused possibly a China
Russia war at some point in time. Maybe
the Russians would have been more
serious about nuking China or maybe not.
We have no idea. A thousand things could
have happened. Yeah. So, and they would
have continued to claim Indian territory
once again. So, yeah, it would not
really have changed much of the India
China equation.
Godliness. Oh man, it's in Hindi.
I'm going to have to read this. Trump.
Trump
tariff war
tariff war.
Oh well. Okay. So, so Trump is very
friendly with the UK and he is investing
he's he's treating the UK as a friend in
the 12 permanuja sin and 12 nuclear
power plants and 30 Arab what is 30 Arab
means billion $30 billion worth of AI
investment. So you see they will do the
same with India also if we simp simply
go down on our knees and beg beg all we
have to do is become an American vasal
allow American military presence on
Indian territory give them some ports
which their military can use allow a few
military bases American military base in
the Himalaya region etc open up the
Indian economy completely to the US then
the Americans will treat us even better
the UK is an American vasal state their
number one vasal state. So obviously
with a vasal you have to be nice, you
know, treat them treat them well. So
there is no surprise in in this at all.
Uh and the UK does want something or
other from Trump. So they've gone out of
of the of their way to make Trump feel
like royalty. Uh the king of England,
what's his name? Charles. He um hosted
Trump for this magnificent apparently
dinner. Trump and his and his you know
the first lady Melania G and the king
and queen of England were there uh King
Charles and Queen Camila and a whole
bunch of other global celebrities and so
on were also there. So the the UK has
gone out of their way to woo Trump and
make him feel like royalty and you're
like the most valued guest you're as as
essentially the emperor of the US that
sort of thing. So Trump is very happy
with the UK UK and so on. Yeah. Prattana
says Israeli strike on Katar fake or
real? Absolutely real. Absolutely real.
It was a real strike on Qatar.
Um
and then there was a deal between Shri
Netanyahuji and a Shri Trump G. And the
deal was that you know we will do this
22 20 point Hamas thing which is
essentially an ultimatum to Hamas that
do what we say otherwise you cease to
exist in Gaza is flattened. So Hamas is
now going ahead with you know the
release of hostages and whatever else it
is. So it's a win for Netanyahu when the
deal is that in exchange for for this
you make a phone call to the mayor of
Qatar sir okay it was a mistake sorry
won't happen again words words kind of
humiliating to a certain extent but
Nathaniel gets what he wants Gaza he
gets Gaza and maybe there is a sweetener
in the deal maybe next is Iran so so the
strike was absolutely real no question
about that okay um Sharma says I am
right-wing arly right-wing as well. But
why the blind support for is by fellow
Indian right-wingers considering they
target journalists aid aids people in
Gaza? It's just because they're fighting
Muslims, Israelites have no love for
India. I don't know why Indians have a
special love for Israel. I have no
hatred for Israel whatsoever. U if the
Israelis are targeting journalists or
whatever in Gaza, it must be because
those journalists and aid people are
handin with Hamas. Anybody
who is handin glove with terrorists is a
fair target. Okay? I am completely with
Israel on this.
I'm completely with Israel on this.
Israel has been the target of terrorist
attacks, relentless terrorist attacks,
horrific terrorist attacks from Hamas.
And the people of Gaza, the people of
Gaza are are are harboring Hamas. They
have voted for Hamas. They've elected
Hamas. And Hamas has this network of
overground people that include
journalists, which includes AIDS people,
that includes doctors and whatnot. Under
hospitals, you have Hamas shelters and
all. So I don't blame Israel one bit for
what they're doing.
I have no issue with what Israel is
doing there. I completely support Israel
in this. The question is what are
Israel's relations with Pakistan? What's
Israel's potential role if any in
Manipur and so on? That's my question.
India and Israel are aligned like 90
95%. There's always going to be some
issues here and there. My I have no
issue with Indians supporting Israel. My
only point is don't blindly support one
nation. Understand everything and don't
put another nation's flag on your on
your on your profile. The only flag on
your profile should be your profile and
don't hero worship some other nation.
The only nation that is worthy of
worship is your own nation. That's my
point. I have nothing against Israel
whatsoever. Of course, there's a
question of what's the deal with between
Israel and Pakistan, for example. See,
let me explain the rational. Let's look
at this from a logical, coldly rational
perspective, not an emotional
perspective. Okay?
The US
is Israel's number one ally. They will
always support Israel no matter what.
Even when you have Barack Obama at the
helm in the US, they will never still do
anything to hurt Israel. Even though
they Obama hated Netanyahu.
So America, the US is Israel's number
one ally. They will never do a thing
that will hurt Israel.
America's vasal is Pakistan.
Okay. So then
what's the relationship between Israel
and Pakistan?
Pakistan is also supporting the Trump
deal in Hamas, the Hamas thing and all
that. And apparently when this Munir
fellow that Pakistani dictator when he
was in Washington recently apparently
when he when the Pakistani embassy
hosted a dinner for him there wasn't
some kind of Israeli presence in that
dinner. So what's the deal between
Israel and Pakistan? We know that
Pakistan officially says that we hate
Israel and we have no diplomatic
relations with Israel but but
there is some connection between Israel
and Pakistan. which is obviously not
good for India. Secondly, the Manipur
story, the Manipur issue, Manipur is a
disaster right now, right? The Man the
Manipur issue is a disaster for India.
It's a disaster for the native people,
indigenous people of Manipur.
Manipur is overrun by foreigners right
now.
Even I mean if they if you have a dark
doesn't make you Indian. Okay?
So these foreigners
have some Israeli connections apparently
because uh last year when some Indian
influencers were brought to Israel on a
tour of Israel, apparently some kooky
rabbi
was brought to meet them by the Israelis
and to explain something about Manipur.
Who the hell is this cookookie rabbi who
is an Israeli citizen? Who the hell is
he to talk about Manipur? So there is
some some connection there. These are my
issues. I completely support Israel on
Gaza. I completely support Israel on the
issue of terrorism
and national security.
I have questions about Pakistan and
Manipur. That's it. Right. Okay.
Tanahesh Pande says Tony Blair may lead
Gaza's interim government under Trump's
plan. Will this end the war or worsen it
since Hamas won't accept foreign
control? My thoughts. Hamas will accept
everything now.
And if they don't,
Gaza will cease to exist. That is the
deal. Hamas has no say anymore in what
happens. Trump has essentially, please
understand this, Trump has essentially
given Hamas
an ultimatum, the final ultimatum. These
are the the points in my proposal, in my
ultimatum. You do this, this, this, then
this, this, this will happen and we will
give you amnesty. If your fighters want
to stay on in Gaza, they can stay on. We
will not target them. If you want your
guys to be moved to some other country,
we will facilitate their transfer to
some third country. But Hamas needs to
give up all the hostages within a
certain deadline, dead or alive. And
then they need to facilitate, they need
to step out of the way, put down their
weapons, all of them, and hand over
power to this interim government. And
Hamas doesn't get to decide who is the
interim government. Hamas is essentially
being dismantled, demilitarized at
least. And if Hamas delays their
acceptance or if Hamas stands against
this and tries to resist this, then
Netanyahu gets a blanch. Go and do
whatever you want. Finish it off. That's
the deal. Who the hell is Hamas going to
be not to accept this anymore? This is
their last chance to stay alive.
Okay, that's it. It's going to happen
one way or the other. If they resist,
Gaza will be flattened.
Entirely flattened. That's the deal.
It's a win for Netanyahu.
IPK1s says Elon Musk recently compared
Indian immigration in the UK to
colonialism in India in a derogatory
way. Why does he tweak his Twitter
algorithm to hate Indians? Elon Musk is
not a friend of India.
Elon Musk is a white supremacist.
Okay.
And he believes that the white race is
is the dominating should be the dominant
race in the world. Elon Musk is very
Gandhian in this aspect.
He's very Gandhian. He echoes the words
of Mr. Gandhi.
Mr. Gandhi said this that I believe that
the white race should be the predominant
race in the British Empire and the
Indians should be number two and the
blacks should be in number three. That's
what Mr. Gandhi wrote on the record in
writing. You can feel free to look it
up. I'm not going to produce the records
over here because the book is somewhere
there and I will have to dig up the
thing.
But that's what Mr. Gandhi said over a
century ago. He didn't say it. He wrote
it in South Africa. So Elon Musk
believes this. Elon Musk believes that
the white race is the predominant race
and should should remain the predominant
race. He believes the white race has
done so much good for the world. Look, I
have personally nothing with against the
white race. I have a lot of people who I
know among the white race. I have
nothing I have nothing against any race
whatsoever.
My issue is with racial supremac
supremacism. Any race, everybody is the
same. We are all human beings. But if
some people believe that because of the
color of the skin or whatever, they're
better than us or somebody else. Well, I
have an issue with that. And there seem
to be a lot of people who have this this
this belief among the white race. I have
an issue with that attitude and that
belief not against any race. Please
understand that. Okay? I have friends
among the white race. So,
so, so Elon Musk is one of these white
supremacists
and he has no uh love for India. Let's
put it that way. So that explains
things. That's why he amplifies this
anti-Indian hate and he amplifies these
false equivalences
that uh if if some kind of false
ridiculous false equivalence
uh which I don't remember exactly what
it was. I'm not going to go and dig up
the tweets now. But yeah, maybe I should
make a separate video on that. Just a
comment on that perhaps. Yeah. So do
remind me about that in the comments
because I've got a thousand things in my
head. Okay. Briesh says, "Should India
take preemptive action against
militants?" Terrorists? It's not
militants, sir. It's not militants, it's
terrorists. Should India take preemptive
action against terrorists to prevent
another Pakistan based attack? The
situation is complicated. Uh if they
give us a just cause for war, we should
go to war and finish the matter
entirely. U but it has to be a cause
that the world will support. Otherwise
they will accuse us of of starting a new
war. So the situation is complicated.
Ideally we should just go and do that.
But the problem is that we have other
nations who are way more powerful than
us who support Pakistan and they are
waiting for us to make a mistake. So we
will unfortunately have to wait for the
right time. If Pakistan gives us the
opportunity which the world will support
by what what kind of opportunity can
Pakistan give us? The unfortunate thing
is that it has to be another terrorist
attack major terrorist attack. That is
something we never want to happen right
but considering the kind of neighbor we
have it may happen unfortunately so if
that's the sort of situation happens
then that gives us the opportunity to
take out Pakistan this time so yeah
that's where we are critical says
hypothetically if the US decides to
withdraw from NATO tomorrow how will
Europe security reconfigure itself or
will a new idea like Russia take the
place
Europe will be lost without the US today
let me explain Why? Let me explain why.
Europe has no leadership.
That's why.
But you will say, "No, but they all have
presidents and prime ministers and all
that. How come Europe has no lead? What
are you talking about? Are you crazy? As
usual, you're delusional. Every nation
has a prime minister or president. What
do you mean by UK Europe has no
leadership?
These
presidents and prime ministers, whoever
they are, they are all puppet appointees
of NATO,
they're all puppet appointees. They
don't really represent their people.
They are implementing policies that are
against their national interests. Give
me, let me give you an example. Do you
think any European nation wants this
large scale immigration coming in from
certain countries?
Do they want these violent men on their
streets who assault the women, local
women and take over the streets and take
over the whole place and become first
class citizens and the natives become
second class citizens? Does does any
European citizen want this in any of the
European nations? They don't want it.
And yet somehow these people keep
winning elections and keep implementing
these policies. These people are not
popular leaders. These are leaders who
have been foisted upon these nations.
The moment Hypothetically the US
withdraws from NATO
these nations will be rudderless.
They will be saddled for a time with
unpopular leaders and there are no
grassroots leaders. They have ensured
that no grassroots leaders emerge who
are genuinely popular. So it's these are
going to be nations without a proper
leadership
and without direction from Brussels,
these leaders will not know what to do
and there's going to be chaos in Europe
if this happens.
What security? Europe. Europe has no
security architecture of its own.
Poland has a decent military. Germany's
military might is entirely dependent on
the US. So is the UK's. France is one
nation that may do well out of this. the
others. Uh so if the US withdraws as the
predominant power in Western Europe,
you're going to be have a situation very
soon in a few years similar to 1914
where all the old rivalries come out
into the open. All the daggers are drawn
and chaos. That's what will happen
hypothetically.
Pratar Dh says Tik Tok acquisition seems
to be related to Israel. It looks like
that. It looks like um this is something
that benefits the US and Israel, Israel
specifically, but it looks like that. I
have not really looked into it, so can't
really comment in detail, but looks like
Mr. Netanyahu was very pleased about the
Tik Tok deal. So, it looks like it's
something that does benefit Israel.
Sanatan
Jigyasu says, "When the US sneezes, the
world catches a cold. How does the US
manipulate and supply
dollar supply and interest rate to steal
from the rest of the world?
Okay, so see the US dollar is the global
reserve currency. It's the currency
that's accepted for most uh
international trade and financial and
monetary transactions, right? Um so who
controls the the supply of the dollar?
Obviously, it's the US, right? They're a
Federal Reserve Bank.
So uh they they determine how how much
volume of US dollars is in circulation
around the world and they can print US
dollars out of thin air if they want
which increases the increases the supply
of the US dollar which devalues which
brings the value down and that makes uh
you know it it affects everything. Uh so
that's how they can manipulate um the
dollar supply
um
and uh interest rates and all that. So
the how to how does it steal from the
rest of the world? Okay, let's address
that. So first of all, no country can
print print the dollar. Only the US can.
So they control that first of all.
Understand that. Now secondly, let's say
the US the US has the world's biggest
debt burden, right? So let's say they
owe let's say a trillion dollars of debt
to for example let's say China
hypothetically.
So the Chinese say give us our money
back. So what can the US do? They can
simply print a trillion dollars
either paper money or digital currency
in the bank in your in your computers in
the main frames or whatever and transfer
that to China. So whenever the US has to
but obviously they'll be have to be
careful about this because if they print
too much money then it'll you know cause
chaos in the world in the in the global
financial economic order but so they can
still do that. So if they want to pay a
trillion dollars of debt back to China
they can simply print a trillion dollars
and give it to China. There you go.
There's your debt paper money. Here's a
bunch of paper. But let's say let's say
the the the let's say South Africa
owes the US a trillion dollars
hypothetically and the US says where's
the money times up. So what South Africa
has to do is that they have to sell
actual
resources or or product or something to
other countries and earn a trillion
dollars from them and then pay that to
the US.
You understand?
So let's say you are a coffee exporting
country and gold exporting country, gold
producer. So you have to give up the
gold that came out of your soil, a
trillion dollars worth of gold to other
countries and get paper money in
exchange and then give that to the US.
You can't print anything. The US can
simply print off their debt. Other
nations have to earn it by by giving up
resources. So that's that's how the US
can acquire all the resources resources
actual resources of of the world by
printing paper money. That's how they do
it. So that's the advantage of having
the having a currency which is the
world's reserve currency.
Um Arun Kumar says you said only
selective Afghan refugees are accepted
but thousands of in Delhi can easily be
identified as non-Indians don't look
like Indians. US HSCR
have registered 15,000 Afghan refugees
in India. I don't know when I have said
this must be like 2 3 years ago. I don't
know what the situation has been like in
the past 2 3 years. If I said something
3 years ago, it doesn't mean it it still
applies today.
Please understand this that times
change. Even something I said 6 months
ago may not apply today because the
situation may have changed. That's the
that is what happens in geopolitics.
Sir, please understand that something
that was spoken even 3 months ago may no
longer be applicable today. The world is
changing.
Do you understand that sir?
Do you understand that things change? I
have no idea what's happened in the past
2 3 years.
Have we accepted more Afghan refugees?
I don't know. So, please understand
this. The world is changing. It's
evolving every single day.
Okay, next.
Amald Desh Pande says in China, if if
China, the US, Saudi Arabia and allies
back Pakistan, how would war unfold?
Which war
in operation Synindur 2.0? Okay. Uh
would India fight alone or get support
from someone? Can you paint a picture of
probabilities?
India will fight alone. Let me already
paint you this picture of probability.
Nobody is going to come and stand with
India.
Not going to happen.
India stands alone. India is alone.
Understand that. You want to have
someone backing you up. You have to give
up your sovereignty and become someone's
vasal.
It is a privilege that you have to fight
alone.
If China has to go to war with the US,
who's going to stand with them? Will
Russia stand with them? It will cause a
nuclear war. Russia will have to be very
careful about this. If the US and Russia
go to war, will China stand with them
and once again with India if if uh India
and Pakistan go to war and the Americans
and Saudis and Chinese back Pakistan, do
you think Russia will come and stand
with us? It's not going to happen. This
is something we have to understand right
now itself. We may be on excellent terms
with Russia, but Russia cannot afford to
get dragged into a war like this. Russia
will not be involved in this. Russia may
sell us weapons and send us supplies or
whatever if required. If required that
they will do beyond that they will not
send their troops to stand with us. Not
going to happen. So let me say this very
clearly right now itself in any future
war with whoever it is India is going to
be fighting alone
but that's fine. That's how it is.
Okay.
Chatanya Pratush says PI Atlas splits
public views. Comet alien craft project
blue beam. How do powers exploit this
for soft or hard power for India? Do we
improve domain awareness or coalition
science? Coalition science to control
narrative your read comet anomaly.
Okay, let's talk about three Atlas.
Yesterday was this object's closest
approach to Mars. Today is what? What's
the date today? Okay, day before
yesterday. Today is the 5th of October.
The 3rd of October was this object's
closest approach to Mars. M A R S Mars.
This object is an interstellar visitor.
It's not an object that is part of the
solar system. It's come from outside.
It's passing through the solar system
and it's very strangely enough passing
exactly along the plane of the solar
system. The plane in which all all the
planets rotate and revolve around the
sun. Right? So there's a plane. The
solar system is is a flat thing. Okay.
All the planets revolve around the sun
in a single plane. And this object is
coming in the exactly the same plane
which is very very interesting, very
unusual, very unusual. Is that a
coincidence?
I mean, is that a coincidence? Maybe
it's a coincidence. Now, the question
is, is this um
is this just a comment or is it
something else? And why is it on an
approach that kind of brings it brings
it very close to Mars and then to
Jupiter while going out? It's not coming
close very close to Earth but it's
approaching it it two days ago it
approached Mars really close by
and while going out it's going to do
another flyby of Jupiter if if the path
if the trajectory remains continues to
be a natural trajectory and some people
are saying that maybe it has some
characteristics that are suspicious
maybe it is outgassing in the wrong
direction if it's a comet then it's coma
its tail
should point away from the sun because
the coma of a comet is caused by
radiation pressure of the solar wind
which excites the molecules and in in in
its u in the comet's composition and
does and causes outgassing and the
outging is directed away from the sun
because because of the pressure from the
solar wind and solar radiation. So a
comet's tail is always pointed away from
the sun. But apparently some people some
scientists are saying that there was
outgassing in the direction of the sun
which looks like a breaking maneuver.
For example, when you have a rocket
booster that's landing, it's going to
spew out its uh it it's uh exhaust
towards the place where it where it's
flowing. Right? So similarly maybe there
is some outgassing maneuver the which
may have caused the which may be
it may its intention may be to slow the
comet down or something but there's no
evidence of that thus far. Hard
evidence. Secondly the comet seems to
have a green glow greenish glow and that
could be because of the nickel plating
that you have on spacecraft or something
that sort of thing. And some images have
come out in the past couple of days that
seem to show that it has a cylindrical
shape which is extraordinarily
suspicious if it is cylindrical.
But is it really cylindrical? I I don't
believe it's cylindrical nonsense. Okay?
Because if you if you take a long
exposure of anything, let me show you
what a long exposure looks like. Okay?
Stars long exposure. It it gives all the
stars an elongated shape. So look here.
Look, stars long exposure.
Let's go. See, this is what a long
exposure looks like. The longer it is,
the longer are the trails of the stars.
Uh if it is a short exposure, what
happens?
Short exposure. Sher.
So if you do a short exposure, all the
stars the the trails look like kind of
like cylinders, right?
Cylinders over here on Earth because we
the Earth is rotating around its axis.
That's why the cylinders are kind of
curved. But in space, if you take a long
exposure, then the cylinder will be
perfectly straight. Straight. So three I
atlas. Three I at
atlas. Um
image. Okay. Three atlas. Let's see. So
if you look at the see if you look at
the latest images um one second
images.
So if you look at images of three Atlas,
you will see that some of the latest
images make it look like
okay. So this is a good image in which
the the the camera is focusing on the
comet which makes everything else look
like cylinders.
So it's clearly something that looks
like a comet and not something with long
with with with a cylindrical shape even
though the background stars look
cylindrical.
But if you don't focus on the common,
you just take a long exposure, then then
even the common will look like a
cylinder. That's the point. So I don't
believe that this cylindrical appearance
is a real thing. It's just an artifact
of how you take the photographs.
Uh so my what's my view? I I think it's
I I don't I have not seen enough
evidence to to to
completely prove that this is possibly
not natural which means maybe it's an
alien spacecraft. I have not seen enough
evidence to prove that. I am not
convinced that it is not an alien
spacecraft. If it changes direction or
something like that then it will be very
suspicious and then I will have to uh
revise my my assessment. Thus far I have
not seen any such uh evidence. How do
powers exploit this? No, nobody's
exploiting this this for anything. This
is nothing to do do with geopolitics. If
it's an actual alien invasion, then
everything changes. But there is no
exploitation of this. How do we improve
domain awareness of and so on. You need
to have your own observatories and all
that. You need to have your own space
based satellites and and Hubble space
telescope like observatories maybe JWST
like observatories. You need to have all
this infrastructure in place then you
can improve your domain awareness.
Ritik Tagi says been watching you since
2021. Thank you so much sir. Thank you.
Uh your talks reignited my love for
history. Outstanding sir. I'm glad to
hear that. Reading the darkening age
now. Um yeah Katherine Nixie. Yes I had
recommended the book. What made Palmyra
so key between Rome and Persia?
Palra that yeah I'm not sure if it was
really key. It was one of the Roman
outposts in the region. It was in Syria
if I am not mistaken. Let's Google it.
Let's go to the map and and check it
out. I think Palmira is in Syria. It's
in the middle of some deserted area.
Pretty barren territory. Let us see.
It's it's a Yeah, pretty interesting
ruin. Yeah.
Palmira
Syria. And zoom. There we have it. So,
if we look at see it's, as you can see,
it's pretty barren. And let's zoom out
to confirm that it is indeed in Syria.
It is indeed in Syria. The So yeah, this
was a Roman uh outpost in the region.
This this territory
uh was under Roman control and to the
east you had the Persian Empire and you
had Roman Persian wars as well. Uh I'm
not sure if Palmer was really a key
outpost or whatever, but it certainly
was. Um,
it it certainly is a very
highly sought-after tourist destination.
So, where's the ruins? This is the
modernday city.
The thing is over here everything looks
like ruins, right? Because the it's in
the desert.
So, where is the pave? Okay, let's see.
Palm ruins.
Okay, here we have it.
So this is the place that is so famous
and obviously this was an ancient Roman
outpost know Roman settlement. Uh I
don't know specifically if it was a
really key settlement or not. I'm not
sure how important it was in the grand
context of things. Roman the Roman
Empire did have a presence over here and
uh that's what brought it into conflict
with the Persian Empire. And you had a
Roman emperor. Who was it? I forget his
name. Who was actually captured by the
Persians and humiliated and so on. Yeah.
Okay. But um but this was a history
question, right? I'm supposed to take
geopolitics questions. I need to remind
myself.
Okay. So I'll only take geopolitics
questions. I have to remind myself.
People will do what they want. People.
Okay. Anyway, Abida Singh says, "Russia,
Ukraine war, Israel, Gaza war, India,
Pakistan war, and their allies all are
interwoven. Doesn't it kind of guarantee
a full-fledged or nuclear war will never
happen as everyone has something to gain
with periodic skirmishes?
Everybody has something to gain and
everybody has something something to
lose. The question is what's the cost
benefit ratio of each of these things
and who turn ends up on the losing side?
Russia Ukraine war there's no nuclear
dimension to this unless NATO gets
involved and NATO will be very careful
not to get involved directly Israel Gaza
there's absolutely no nuclear dimension
unless all the other neighboring
countries get involved which they are
very they are not going to do that India
Pakistan sure there could be a nuclear
dimension but then even now even in
India Pakistan I doubt it unless the US
authorizes the use of its nuclear
weapons because most likely it's
becoming increasingly clear now the
Pakistanis
whatever nuclear warheads they they
have, they are probably American nuclear
warheads.
So if the Americans approve a Pakistani
nuclear strike, well then a nuclear war
can happen and even then it's not a
global nuclear war. It's just India
Pakistan and India gets damaged but
Pakistan ceases to exist.
So
so everybody has something to gain.
Everybody has something to lose. If
India and Pakistan really go to a
full-fledged war, Pakistan has
everything to lose. we have some
something to lose. It will significantly
certainly damage damage India to some
extent but Pakistan will completely
cease to exist. Um
so does it mean that
um does it mean doesn't it kind of
guarantee a full-fledged nuclear war
will never happen? It guarantees
nothing. One little miscalculation we
can set off a global conflration
of. So first of all let's understand
what do we mean by a full-fledged
nuclear war. India Pakistan having a
full-fledged nuclear war will end in
like 10 minutes with the damage on one
side and complete destruction on another
side and it's over. India China could be
much worse. It'll significantly damage
both countries.
Um
China Russia less likely to happen.
India China also less likely to happen.
Israel versus its neighbors Israel wins.
The only nuclear war we need to the the
entire world should be worried about is
US versus Russia. That's what we need to
worry about. Um that's what the whole
world needs to worry about. And there is
no guarantee it won't happen. Absolutely
no guarantee. One miscalculation can set
of a disaster.
Tanmadesh Pand says there's a theory
that India and China have an unspoken
pact that in that China gets Taiwan,
India gets P with no opposition on both
sides any truth to this. Who has come up
with this theory?
Who? Who? How do we know there's this
unspoken fact? How do we know? If there
is, let's say hypothetically a pack like
this,
it is going to be top secret. If it does
exist, how will this theory come out?
Then these theories are are pedled
by various influencers and so on. I I
don't know who has Okay, first of all,
let me say I've not heard of this. I
personally have never said such a thing.
And if somebody has come up with a
theory and all that, well, good for
them. I am not going to speculate.
I have no information that there is such
a such a pact, unspoken pact or
whatever. I have no such information and
I have no connections high up in in in
in Delhi or Beijing by the way. Okay? So
I I am not going to be the person who
will know about such a thing if it does
exist and I will refrain from
speculating. These are these are wild
speculations.
Yeah. Does it make sense? Now that's a
different story. Does it make sense for
both the nations to have such a pack?
How could China guarantee that India
gets PK? Tell me how does China let me
blow a gigantic hole in this theory.
huge hole that the theory cannot recover
from.
If Pakistan is China's vasal and if
China controls Pakistan, then China can
guarantee that India gets P if India
doesn't interfere in the Taiwan matter.
Sure. But Pakistan is an American vasal.
China has no control over Pakistan
today. How can China guarantee that
India gets P?
This theory has no legs to stand on.
Okay, so I have no idea who originated
this theory. Which influencer or which
YouTuber came up with this theory? This
theory doesn't have legs to stand on.
Okay.
Project Smiling Buddha says, "I know it
with high level of confidence that the
West is working on denying 6G mobile
technology to China and India and moving
all the 6G development work to Romania
and Portugal. Are we ready? What's my
suggestion to the government? Develop
our own 6G technology." That's my simple
suggestion. I have no idea by the way.
Okay. Maybe you you have some
information. Okay. Um that's good.
That's good in case you have the
information. Um so let's say
hypothetically if the west wants to deny
6G mobile technology to India and China
and by by diverting to Romania,
Portugal, whatever, what should India
India should develop its own 6G
technology? Did we buy 5G technology
from somebody or did we develop it on
our own? I'm pretty sure we developed it
entirely ourselves, right? Or did we did
we acquire 6G technology, buy it from
somewhere? I'm not sure. I have not
looked into it. But my suggestion would
be very simple. Develop the 6G
technology eventually 7G, 8G, 9G, 10G,
6G, whatever entirely on our own. We
should not be dependent on other nations
for technology.
It is a critical Achilles heel if we are
dependent on the other nations. it it
means that we are technologically not
sovereign if that is the case. So my
suggestion is very simple. India should
develop all this technology entirely on
its own inhouse. That's all.
Samura says I've been your listeners
since 2020. Wow that's a long time.
Thank you so much. Thank you so much.
Good to have you sir. Thank you. Uh
listening to you has expanded my
thinking and helped me see the world
differently. Deep respect and gratitude
for your work. Thank you so much. Thank
you so much sir. uh truly a pleasure to
have uh you know it's a privilege to to
have viewers who've been watching me for
such a long time hearing listening to me
to listening to me for such a long time.
It's a privilege. It's a privilege to
have one person spend a little bit of
time listening to you. It's a privilege
very few people have unfortunately. So I
am very grateful to you and everybody
else who does take the time to listen to
me. I'm very grateful to all of you.
Thank you so much.
Teentox Dharma says, "Do you not think
that the US is the reason why there is
no World War II? Because the US doesn't
let anyone rise to its status? Is it
better to live under a unipolar world?
Is the U US a reason the reason why
there's no World War II?"
So, let's once again
try and define what World War II looks
like.
What is the definition of a world war?
Let's say the First World War. Was it
really a world war? It was the European
war which spilled out to Africa and Asia
to some extent. India got involved
because we we were a slave of the of the
British.
It was not really a world war. It was a
foreign war for India that we were
dragged into. The second world war was a
continuation of this European tribal
war. And once again we were dragged into
it because we were a slave of the UK.
And this time the war spread to other
parts of the world including Asia
because of the Japanese involvement and
so on. So world war is a war in which
everyone's involved. Most major nations
in the world are involved. And the third
world war will obviously use use 21st
century technologies which is going to
be devastating. Is the US the reason why
this third world war doesn't happen? No.
know if a third world war happens it
will be because of the US actually. Uh
so it's not like there's always a
balance of power in the world and when
you have more and more powerful weapons
then then becomes more dangerous for a
world war to happen or for the major
powers to go to war. The US obviously
will try its best not to allow anyone to
rise to its status. But today you have
nations that can
well Russia hasn't risen to the the
status of the US but Russia can
completely finish the US and also get
finished in in exchange. Uh so I I don't
I would not agree that the US is the
reason why there is no World War II. If
a World War II happens, it will be
because of the US. Is it better to live
under a unipolar world? Absolutely not.
It means you are living under slavery.
But we had enough of this my dear
friends.
Okay. Hitman says, "Big fan of your
work." Thank you so much, sir. Thank you
so much. And thank you so much. Thank
you so much for being a me member. I
really appreciate that, sir. Thank you.
Sam Aurora says, "Let's say you're the
PM of the country. What might be
currently stopping you from reforming
our education system, which is the root
cause of most our problem? Most most of
our problem." See, this is not a
geopolitical question. Let me take it
briefly though because the education
system does impact geopolitics.
What's stopping me from reforming the
education system? The fact that the
prime minister is not powerful enough.
The prime minister doesn't have the
power to reform every educational board
in the in the country. The prime
minister doesn't have the power to tell
x state or y state or zed state what
kind of education system needs to be
implemented there. India is this weak
federal system
and the center doesn't have sufficient
power to do all this.
and the and the the if you have a
coalition government then you need the
the the support of other parties and if
they don't like what you're doing they
will take they'll withdraw support and
even if you have a full majority and you
have MPs from different states and if
some states don't like your educational
reforms then those MPs may revolt or
something and you may lose your majority
there are all these issues in India the
main problem is the system the kind of
system that we have and I can distill
that into one sentence the prime Prime
Minister doesn't have sufficient power.
That's the reason. Okay. Right. Hitman.
Namaste.
Thank you so much, sir. Thank you so
much. Really appreciate that. Thank you,
sir. Perseus says, "I am curious. Is the
deep state strictly a US thing or does
their power extend to the whole world
more importantly to India and do they
have or do they have their
counterparts?" Okay.
the deep state.
So the deep state when we talk about the
deep deep state we're talking about the
US
um what is this US deep state it is the
extra democratic extra constitutional
power center that seems to exist in
exist in the US see technically on paper
the US president is the most powerful uh
person in the country who runs the
country with the help of his cabinet
right and all the other inst
institutions and organs of the of the
government
are in support of this essentially right
that's what it says on paper and the
president represents the will of the
people that sort of thing but actually
there seems to be another power center
somewhere that is more powerful than the
president for example I can give you a
very clear example the uh US federal
reserve bank the president of the US
doesn't control the federal reserve
the federal reserve as a private bank.
Imagine the RBI of India is a private
bank. We don't know who really owns it.
That would mean that that India is is
privately owned. India's economy is
privately owned. That's what that's what
it would mean. So the American economy
is privately owned by some people and we
we are not told who they are. So clearly
there is a deep state that itself is an
indicator that there is something that
doesn't that beyond what meets the eye
and so on. So there seems to be a small
number of people who are super powerful,
way more powerful than the president of
the US and the US president has to be
very careful not to cross them. Um does
their power extend to the whole world?
Their power extends way beyond the US.
Way beyond the US in various shapes and
forms.
Uh does it extend to India? They have
resources in India. That's let's put it
that way. They have resources in India.
Assets. They have assets in India.
Do they have counterparts? I don't know
about counterparts. They have assets.
They certainly have assets in India.
That's as much as I can say. I I I will
I will not venture to elaborate beyond
that.
Milan has no question but All right.
Thank you so much. I really appreciate
that. Thank you very much, sir. Thank
you very much. Or ma'am, don't know.
Thank you. Dib Yayan says your thoughts
on the recent PJK unrest. Okay. So
recently there's been this new wave of
unrest in Pakistan occupied Jammu and
Kashmir.
So it it's clear that the people of
Pakistan occupied Jammu and Kashmir and
Gilgit Baltistasan are not happy with
the Pakistani occupation. They're not
happy. Why are they unhappy? Because the
government of Pakistan has done nothing
for them. no progress, no development,
no opportunities, no economic
opportunities. Um, nothing. There's no
hospitals, there's no schools, colleges,
there's no infrastructure, there's poor
electricity, no drinking water, um,
oppression by the Pakistani army, all of
that.
And they can see across the line of
control what the situation is. so much
progress, so much development,
so many more economic opportunities and
so much more and they aspire to have the
same level of development and progress
and quality of life and all that. So
that's why they are so unhappy and they
are not represented in the Pakistani
parliament as far as I know and they
they are essentially under foreign
occupation. So they are deeply upset
about that and that's why they keep on
protesting from time to time. Now let me
explain something to you all to all of
you. Are you under the impression that
the people of Pakistan occupied Jammu
and Kashmir want to reintegrate with
India? Are you under the impression
somehow that they have some love for
India?
Do do you do you all really think so
that they love India? They want to
return to India.
They want to be independent. They have
no love for India. They don't want to
reintegrate with India. They just want
to be
free from the Pakistani occupation.
understand that very clearly. Okay,
please let's not live in some in case
some of you are living in some fantasy
land or some fantasy world or La La
Land, let me bring you back to the real
world. The people of Pakistan occupied
Jammu and Kashmir have absolutely no
love for India. Understand that.
Milan says, "Can the global order
survive for much longer with the current
convergence of major p power rivalries,
intensifying local conflicts and the
advent of AI. World War II possibility
the century the World War II possibility
is always there. I hope it doesn't
happen. Um there are there is
understanding between various nations
that have the capac capability to
destroy the world. But uh one little
miscalculation can set off a world war.
Uh, can the global order survive much
longer with the convergence of major
power rivalries, intensifying local
conflicts and the advent of AI? See,
what's happening right now is a
restructuring of the world order. It is
not happening randomly. It is not
happening spontaneously. It is being
engineered.
The global order is being re-engineered.
the tariffs that Trump is imposing on
various nations on an ad hoc basis on a
bilateral basis it completely dismantles
the the WTO structure that you had World
Trade Organization the so-called
rules-based world order everything is
being dismantled by Trump they created
that system and they are dismantling it
now that's number one okay number two we
have all these fault lines that have
opened up Russia Ukraine Russia is
eventually going to partition in Ukraine
and take over Ukraine Whenever it
happens, it'll happen. Russia is going
to prevail in the Ukraine war. The
Russia US rivalry is now out in the
open. It's naked. NATO is a US proxy.
It's a US puppet. So is the EU. And the
Ukraine war is a proxy war between
Russia and NATO. And NATO is a proxy of
the US. So it's actually a Russia US war
with a double proxy layer.
So that rivalry is out in the open now.
And the objective was to destroy Russia.
Did not happen. It actually ended up
strengthening Russia. But it's kind of
isolated Russia to some extent. and
Russia was prepared for that.
Now there's other um intensifying local
conflicts. The other one is Gaza. Gaza
is a small thing. It's it's going to be
resolved now. But Gaza, the resolution
of the Gaza conflict and the dismantling
of Hamas. It is going to possibly set
the prelude for something to happen to
Iran.
Iran could be next.
So let's say the Americans do a regime
change in Iran and also do a regime
change in Venezuela.
Then the world becomes cleanly cut into
two pl two two two groups.
The US-led world order the US and its
vasals which is the whole of Africa the
whole of the Middle East Iran gone
Venezuela going the whole of Latin
America Central America and the
Southeast Asia Japan South Korea all of
that. That's on one one side and
obviously EU and NATO. All of that is
with the US. On the other hand, you have
Pakistan and China and North Korea.
What is left? India has left. Then they
got they're going to come after India in
some way or the other. That is what's
happening. AI is obviously a big player
in this. So that is the deal. I suspect
I fear that Iran could be next in the
crosshairs once the Gaza issue is
resolved which will be resolved soon
enough.
Yeah. They will solve Iran and if if
Israel and the US launch a war on Iran,
do you think Russia and China will come
and will be in a position to come and
save Iran? I doubt it very much.
So that is how the dominoes seem to be
in the process of rolling possibly.
Yeah. Let's see.
Aravshaw says global hyperbolicity.
Global hyperbolicity is assumed in in
very quantum gravity theory.
This makes sense for a well-defined
initial value formalism that heavily
relies on cosmic censorship. Could there
be more work in relaxing assumptions?
Okay sir, we are not discussing science
today. Sir, we are discussing
geopolitics. If I start taking questions
from every field, then the people the
viewers who have come for geopolitics,
they will not be happy. Sir, let's take
these questions about the time. Sir,
please
I'll only talk take geopolitics
questions today. Nilles Patil says, "Was
judgment of Indian judge in Tokyo trials
incorrect? After all, Japanese did
commit those crimes and tortures." I
have not read the judgment.
Um,
what was the judgment
and and and
figure out what was said, I can't really
answer the question. Maybe we can look
it up.
Okay, let's quickly try and summarize
what the judgment was.
Um, Judge Rada Binodal
Tokyo trial
trial
judgement summary.
Okay, let's see what does it say.
dissenting judgment acquitted all
Japanese defendants arguing that the
charges of excessive war and crimes
against humanity were based on expost
factor principles and that the tribunal
represented the victim's justice. He
contended that no prior international
law prohibited aggressive war and that
insufficient evidence proved direct
individual responsibility for
atrocities.
um past descent though a minority view
became has become a significant critique
of the post-war legal proceedings and
was supported by Japan which honored him
and so on. So the key arguments no prior
law for aggressive war. Paul argued that
crimes against peace and aggressive war
were not established offenses under
international law at the time Japan
engaged in the conflict. So that's post
X facto. Western nations had
historically exercised this right
without prohibition. Uh and therefore it
was unjust to try only the powers for
it. Lack of proof for individual
responsibility. Evictus justice exp post
postf factor application of no hello
allow absolutely critique of yeah okay I
completely agree with Shri Radha binod
pal's judgment absolutely
absolutely agree with him this is
victor's justice this is expost facto
justice come on
I completely agree with him godliness uh
sorry I had to ask my last question on
UK US in Hindi as YouTube was not
allowing it was was not allowing ing me
to ask the same question in English.
Wow. Really?
Okay. So, it was maybe some words may
have triggered its censorship algorithm
or something. It happens. I'm I'm sorry.
I can't control that. So, okay. I
totally understand why you had to do
that then in that case. Okay. Puroptam
Pradans is off topic, but no,
I'm not going to watch Kantara or
whatever. I I have no interest in that.
And I'm hearing that there are some
possibly some missionary propaganda in
that.
Uh yeah. So I I haven't watched Canara
one. I'm not watching Canara 2. Sorry.
Sorry.
Uh Dib Yan Dib Yayan says India's GDP
growth is decent despite the global
turbulence. How confident are you of
Vixit Bharat if we continue having
strong governance and reforms? I am
super confident of a Vixit bat by 2047.
If we have strong governance and if we
have actual reforms.
What do I mean by actual reforms?
Please end the hypothetical alleged
corruption in the country. Without that,
nothing is going to change. Secondly,
the reservations are going to destroy
the country. We need a fully
meritocratic system. Thirdly, the
education system is critical. If you
don't reform it, nothing's going to
change. Indians will remain living in La
La Land and remain crippled mentally.
Without these three major changes, there
is going to be no wix bat. Without these
three major changes, one alleged
corruption, two meritocracy and end of
reservations. And third, the reforms of
the education system. Without these
three reforms, India is doomed to
mediocrity. What vixit bar? No vikit
bat. Nothing.
SL says, okay, what is this? CN versus
China versus Russia
after US decline in future border clash
ahead
US decline. Are you assuming there's
going to be US decline in the future?
It's all empires decline but it could
take 200 years.
So yeah, see China and Russia are
natural rivals. They're not natural
they're not natural allies. They're
natural adversaries. So if there's a US
decline, China and Russia will once
again resume their rivalry and
adversarial relationship which could
cause border clashes certainly.
Anonymous scientist Bisar Mu Bisar, how
powerful and influential is the pharma
lobby in geopolitics?
Well, that's quite a interesting
question. The farmer lobby is the US
farmer lobby. It's super influential in
the US and the US is the most important
player globally in geopolitics. So it is
indeed super influential globally as
well
and it tried
for example Fiser tried pushing its
horrific vaccine worldwide.
They wanted India to to approve the
usage of the Fiser vaccine but we
obviously refused without proper trials
independent trials and they refused to
have independent trials because they
knew what will happen. Uh
Shane War died.
Yeah. Was he someone who would just die
like that? I'm sure he took that
vaccine. What a loss. Anyway, so farmer
lobby is is pretty powerful, you know,
internationally. It doesn't actually
affect geopolitical outcomes, but it is
a significant player globally because of
the US dominance in the world. Nandanda
Kizor says why the slave US is hostile
to India but master Israel is not. So
you are asking me to answer this
question assuming that Israel is the
master of the US. I am not going to
assume that Israel is the master of the
US.
Maybe the US is the dominant power in
the relationship. I am not clear about
who is the dominant power in this
relationship. So yeah. So yeah. So I
can't answer the question assuming what
you are asking me to assume I can't
assume that
Kumar Patel says does 25 cr Muslims
include 10 crore illegal Bangladesh I
have no idea I have no idea and this is
not a geopolitical question sir this is
an internal matter of India I don't
comment about that obviously it's a
problem the the 10 cr illegal
Bangladeshes uh I'm not sure if that is
included in the whatever demographic you
are referring to sir
Kunal Krish says do you think India like
America is turning into a police state?
No.
No. Earlier we saw fewer cops in the
roads than we do today. No. No. India is
not turning into a police state. It's
not. To know what a police state is like
go to the US. Go to certain European
countries. Then you will know what a
police state looks like.
India is nowhere close to being a police
state. India is a very relaxed country.
And you should be grateful that we are
to some extent at least.
I mean in the US the cops can shoot you
for anything.
They can exercise that that right to
shoot you. No questions asked and even
if they're wrong nothing happens. That
is not really the case in India. We are
far from being that. So no it's not the
case. Diban says your forecast of UK and
EU economies given their worsening
situation. France, Germany, UK have high
deficit. Will they see worsening
standards of living?
They will. Their economies are not doing
great. I don't see the e economies
reviving anytime soon. I don't see the
economies booming, forget not booming,
even doing okay.
See, it's it's very simple. All human
activity
from the dawn of human history 400,000
years ago, all human activity depends on
one thing and one thing only, energy.
Access to energy.
When our
hunter gatherer ancestors from 300,000
years ago, when they went hunting, they
had to spend energy, muscle, muscular
energy. And if they did not hunt on
time, they would die of starvation. Then
once we started living in villages and
groups and all that, we had to build
huts or whatever, that needed the
expenditure of mus muscle power. Then
when you had two rival tribes fighting
each other for territory, that involved
the use of muscle power, which is
energy. And then you had ranged weapons
and all that, which was again the
expenditure of energy. Then if you want
to build walls and all, it needs energy.
If you want to uh in the medieval era
when you had warfare on horses once
again it's energy in the force of form
of horsepower then you had other forms
of energy like rockets and
guns
and if you want to travel long distances
you have to burn coal petrol whatever so
every human activity depends on energy a
major nation's economy it depends on the
availability of energy and today the EU
nations are are deliberately sabotaging
their energy availability. They are
switching to coal. They have shut down
shut down their nuclear power plants.
Germany did that. Um and and even if you
do that, if you have access to cheap
Russian gas, you're fine. But they've
shut that down also. So when you don't
have this reliable,
you know, supply, plentiful supply of
cheap energy, you're not going to do
well.
And so we have all these issues that you
have in Europe. So I don't see those
economies doing well anytime soon. I
think the situation is going to worsen.
The standards of living will decline.
There's going to be more strife in
society with the immigration, illegal
immigration which is now legalized and
whatnot and the demographic replacement
that's happening in Europe. I think the
way things are going, Europe is going
downhill and I don't see a way out of it
for Europe the way things are right now.
So yeah, long-term I don't have a good
good prognosis for the UK and for the EU
and the UK is in the same boat as the
EU. Even if they have done Brexit, it
doesn't make any difference. The
prognosis isn't good at all. Abishek
says, uh, Indians think Obama is some
great president, but could you please
explain why Obama is the same as any
other American president? My question
is, what did Obama achieve?
What did he achieve? What are his
achievements?
I mean, if you what did Ronald Reagan
achieve? Well, you could say that he
kind of presided over the over the
weakening of the USSR, which eventually
led to its decline. He was the last
great president of the US who, you know,
boosted the American economy in various
ways. Uh then George Bush the senior, he
did not do much obviously. Clinton, what
did he achieve? Nothing much.
Nothing really much. And what did Omama
achieve? What did George W. Bush
achieve? Well, he he won the second oil
war, the second Gulf War. He had Saddam
Hussein captured and executed. He
oversaw the the occupation of
Afghanistan.
Then he launched this war of war on
terror on the world and he destroyed
Iraq. So great achievements. What did
Obama do? Well, the one achievement is
that he destroyed Libya.
It's it's during his uh tenure that
Libya was destroyed, wasn't it? Obama.
Uh so I'm not sure what Obama achieved.
What is his great achievement? I'm not
sure. Nothing great. The American
economy did not do really well at all.
Obamacare was a flop. So overall, he did
not achieve anything special, anything
specific. The only distinction he has is
that he is the first non-white
full non-completely white American
president. was only half half white, not
completely white, right? 50% black, 50%
white. That's the only distinction that
he has. And he had a female secretary of
state for a while. Hillary Rodm Clinton,
that's about it.
Okay. Anonymous scientist says, should
India tweak its nuclear deterrence
policy in the future and make it more
barbaric like the US nuclear policy or
is the current policy good? I don't know
what the current policy is. Whatever the
stated policy is, it doesn't matter.
What the real policy is is what matters.
And that's something you don't disclose
to anyone.
See, you're not obliged to spell out
exactly what your nuclear policy is.
Let's say you state that we have a no
first use policy.
It's a it's a statement you've made, but
when let's say in the future you go to
war, you may decide to change the policy
on the spot. So these statements don't
matter. Please understand this. The
Chinese also have a no first use policy.
But let's say they are in a tight corner
someday. You think they will hesitate to
from you know hesitate to use nuclear
weapons first if needed if it isn't if
it gives them an advantage. They will
not. So all these policy statements and
all you have to take them with table
tablespoonfuls of salt.
These these statements are just for
public consumption.
Okay. So I don't know what the current
policy is. I'm sure it's good. That's
what I can tell you. Wamshi Khaleim
says, "How when slash how could the
dollar lose its reserve currency
status?" Ah, Vami Khim, when and how
could the US dollar lose its reserve
currency status?
If a significant number of highly
relevant nations
decide to collectively start using a
different currency or a different set of
currencies then the US dollar becomes
you know less viable. It it's it's on
shaky ground. Now let's say the BRICS
nations for example
I don't know how many n which are the
BRICS nations today we have way more
than before right uh which are the BRICS
nations bricks nations.
So obviously we have the top five
Brazil, Russia, India, China, South
Africa. And now we have Egypt, Ethiopia,
Indonesia, Iran, Saudi Arabia and the
UAE. Well, UAE and Saudi Arabia are
actually US allies. Indonesia also is.
Egypt also is. So okay. Oh, what is
this? End of the dollar. That's funny.
Okay. So if you have these nations,
forget about the other other ones.
Brazil, Russia, India, China, South
Africa. Even if India, Russia, China and
Brazil alone decide to stop using the US
dollar, that is a big setback to the US.
Obviously, they will go to war. The US
will go to war against us if we do that.
But yeah, if something like that
happens. So BRICS today accounts for for
more of the world's GDP than the G7
nations. So if the BRICS nations
actually decide to do this to stop using
the US dollar and start using maybe the
Russian ruble or the Chinese yuan or
maybe the rubal yuan and rupee
collectively
then that could be a huge setback to the
US but that's a very dangerous decision
to take because the US will go to war
against you. So it's not going to happen
anytime soon. It will not happen
suddenly. Maybe it will happen gradually
if it does happen or maybe it won't
happen at all for the next 50 years. Who
knows? Can't say.
Uh I think the probability is higher
that this will happen gradually and
maybe BRICS will take the lead but when
I'm not sure. Animesh says happy. Well
happy Dashara to you as well and to
everybody else. Why does the US offer
unconditional support to Israel? Is
there an alleged is influential Israeli
lobby and what makes it so powerful? Why
isn't US support for Europe as strong?
Well, there seems to be a powerful and
influential Israel Israeli lobby. That's
not alleged. it seems to exist. Um there
is this book by
John Mirshimer. Let me see
John Mirshimer
uh Israel
lobby. Okay, there's this book.
So this gentleman John Mir Shimemer is a
very highly respected professor
of political science at the University
of Chicago
and he has written this book the Israel
lobby and US foreign policy. So there
clearly is an Israel lobby in the US
which seems to be pretty influential and
powerful in the US political circles and
maybe it is one of the reasons why the
US offers this tremendous essentially
unconditional support to Israel, right?
Uh so yeah clearly there is an Israel
lobby
and uh if if such a if such a reputable
and highly respected professor writes an
entire book about this clearly it exists
right so that possibly could explain why
the US you know offers this
unconditional support to Israel why
isn't US support for Europe as strong
well the US sees Europe as an asset to
be used Europe essentially is under de
facto US occupation. Uh many of the
European many of the EU nations or many
of the NATO nations are under US
occupation which means that the US has
troops on those nations territories and
military bases on those nations
territories in some of the nations like
the Netherlands and and Turkey etc. the
US has actually deployed nuclear weapons
on these nations territory.
So and and when it comes to the EU, not
NATO but EU, then EU is run by Brussels.
EU is is ruled by Brussels and Brussels
is in the pocket of Washington DC. So
the US sees Europe as an asset, not as
an ally, but it sees Israel probably as
an ally, not as an asset. So that's the
difference.
Satan Jigasu says, "What's the
difference between third, fourth, fifth
generation fighter planes? What specific
trade-offs do they offer? Is newer
generation always better in all
situations? Educate me.
Okay. Um, it's about significant
technological leaps every time. So, f
the first generation is the basic
jet engine fighter plates. The second
generation is your MIG 21s.
Is Mig 21 second or third generation?
It's all about technological leaps every
time. So the fifth generation fighter
planes are stealth fighter planes that
can destroy targets at standoff ranges
like 200 300 km ranges.
So that depends on the kind of missiles
they have and also stealth
characteristics. Fourth generation
fighter planes typically don't have
stealth characteristics and they don't
have the the capability to destroy
targets at standoff ranges. So let's say
you have a dog fight between two planes.
If it's a third generation fighter
planes, then they will have to come into
close proximity to launch short range
missiles at each other or cannons
that sort of thing. Fourth generation
fighter planes will be able to fight at
longer ranges and eliminate targets from
long longer ranges maybe 20 30 km.
>> Fifth generation fighter planes can do
that at like 300 km ranges and they will
be stealthy. That's the kind of thing.
So let's quickly take a look at examples
of fighter plane generations.
Examples of of uh fighter plane
generations.
Let's see. First, second, third, fourth,
fifth. First generation me. Okay. Mig 15
was the first generation. Yes. Second,
second generation is MIG 21. So we we
were until recently using second
generation fighter planes. Mig 21s.
Third generation is F4 Phantom and
F-16s. Fourth generation F-15s Euro
Fighter Typhoon. Fifth generation is a
F2 Raptor Raptor F-35 Sukcoy 57 and the
Rafal is between the fourth and the
fifth generation.
So these are not hard and fast
classifications obviously. Messarith
ME262.
So okay the first generation was a
straightforward jet engine fighter
planes. The second one was supersonic
flight. Second generation, third
generation is multi-roll capabilities,
advanced electronics missiles. Fourth
generation is high performance,
maneuverable, four and a half
generation, so forth, advanced avionics,
limited stealth. Fifth generation is
stealth, low observable technology and
super cruise.
And sixth generation is artificial
intelligence, remote piloting and so on.
Yeah, that's about it. Yeah.
Yeah. Next. Utios says you said
something about making a battle video on
the battle of 10 kings in Yamna
connection. Can we expect it or have
you? I have not made it sir and this is
not a history session. Let us not
discuss history today sir. Please sir
let me keep reminding everybody I beg
you all don't ask me history questions
in this live stream. We are discussing
geopolitics today. Please I have not
made the video and I don't have any
plans of making it anytime soon right
now at this point in time. Geopolitic
lub is full support sir. Thank you very
much sir. Thank you very much. Very much
appreciated. Sar
Utios is once again asking a question
about
can education system be a godge of
measuring standards in a nation or
country or even its destiny? What's the
destin destiny of India if education
system does not change? Well, I'll take
this question even if it's not entirely
about geopolitics because it's about
about destinies of nations. The
education system is indeed of the the
most important goge of measuring the
standards of a nation and it is
something that is a good indicator
reliable indicator of the long-term
destiny of a nation. Yeah, it doesn't
tell you everything about the destiny of
a nation but it tells you about the
standards the intellectual standards
mental standards etc. of a nation.
So what's the destiny of India if the
education system does not change?
mediocrity
um no visual guruess no superguruess no
superpower status ever mainly mediocrity
and vasal state state stat status in the
future
d says how can India create its own
narrative and grow also
create its own narrative you know what's
a narrative it's propaganda there are
nations that are super powerful in
propaganda like the US like China even
Pakistan is good at propaganda how can
India create it own propaganda by
creating its own media outlets similar
to the BBC, CNN and so on, right? Why
don't we have it? The Chinese have
multiple such media outlets in print in
in audiovisisual medium and so on. We
have nothing. We simply don't bother to
have it. We have no ambition. Our
government seems to lack the ambition to
to put forward India's uh point of view
with confidence.
Our government is simply not invested in
this. 11 years they they've been power.
They've done nothing about this. Big
fail. Big fail. Huge fail. So what India
can do is create these media outlets
similar to the BBC, similar to the to
CNN, similar to Deutsche Wellness of
France France 24, similar to what the
CCT and the Chinese the have Shininoa
and so on. We have done nothing of this.
We simply don't care. That's one thing
we can do. Secondly, take the social
media battle and war seriously.
If the Americans and Pakistanis and
Chinese can have used millions of bots
to push their propaganda, why can't
India do it? Why are we not fighting
this battle? It's like we simply don't
care. So that's what India can do. But
the government seems to have no ambition
of doing that. Arismantic says, can we
initiate an emergency and enforce
critical reforms, restructure the
bureaucracy and change the parameters of
the constitution of India to suit India?
Theoretically it's possible I suppose.
I mean Mrs. Indra Gandhi did some of
these changes when she implemented the
emergency what 1975 or something. Um she
did change the constitution.
She did she did she restructure the
bureaucracy? I'm not sure about that.
She did implement significant changes
limited changes but significant changes
at the time. Uh I suppose it it could be
possible. Yeah. To initiate an emergency
and enforce critical reforms.
Um theoretically it's possible. Will the
reforms be long-lasting once the
emergency ends or will there be chaos in
the country? Can't really say about
that.
But if Mrs. Gandhi could do it, maybe
some other leader could also possibly do
it. Yeah. Uh Vinay Johi says, "How do
you compare Middle Eastern spring with
Indian spring?" There is no Indian
spring.
Are you talking about the weather? Are
you talking about the geopolitical uh
the regime change attempts
the Arab spring right we we don't have
any Indian spring there has been no such
attempt to do a regime change in India
at least thus far we may not be far from
that maybe they will try something these
these days they call it a genzi thing
right these these days there are genzi
revolutions happening in the world this
is nothing but another color revolution
thing they're just giving it a new
terminology new name new coat of paint
new mask There is no Indian spring thus
far but it could happen.
Vivik Singh says Israel Iran in Indo
Park 2.0 seems imminent. How do you
think China will play its cards here?
They hate India but their main enemy is
the US. The Chinese don't hate India.
They simply see India as an
inconvenience and they see India as a
potential threat as a potential rival.
They know that India is not a hgemonic
nation that will come that will tomorrow
morning try and make a move on Beijing.
India is doesn't have any ambition of
invading China and and taking territory.
They know that. But as long as India
exists as this big unified country, it's
it's a rival to China in in a variety of
ways
and if India is broken up or whatever it
suits China. Um so first understand the
Chinese don't hate India. They don't
respect India too much because India is
a mediocre nation today. I think I don't
think anyone can deny it. India is a
nation of low standards today. A
mediocre nation. The Chinese see India
as a stoogge of the west which we are to
a very large extent. A mentally
colonized nation with no self-respect.
All of this is what the Chinese say
about India and they are mostly correct
about in their assessment about India.
Okay.
Please let's let's be realistic. The
Chinese are right.
Now, Israel, Iran could happen soon,
possibly. Uh, India Park 2.0 could
happen soon, possibly. How do I think
China will play its cards here?
If Iran is on the verge of going down,
what could China do? Nothing much
actually. I mean, you had a first round
of that recently.
uh the Israelis they they took out some
Iranian IRGC generals and the Americans
bombarded various Iranian nuclear
processing facilities
and the Iranians they did launch some
missile attacks on Tel Aviv and so on
which did cause you know visible damage
non-negligible damage for sure but can
Iran stave off a full-fledged war, a
full-fledged invasion of Iran. Not sure.
See, when when this first round happened
between Israel and Iran and Iran was
getting kind of pounded, the Chinese
stayed out of it. So did so did the
Russians, right? So if there is a
full-fledged war, an invasion of Iran,
let's say, hypothetically,
will China try and come to Iran's
rescue? How can they do it? Even if they
want to, can they do it? How can they
do? They can't.
Russia isn't far from Iran actually,
just north of the Caspian Sea. So,
Russia is more in a position to
intervene if they think it's worthwhile.
But even that's a question mark. So, I
think China will mostly sit it out.
Russia may possibly think of perhaps
getting involved. They may consider the
possibility, but China most likely will
stay out of it. Yeah. Um Yeah.
Utios says when asked about interference
in US elections in a 2018 interview
said that the US policy towards Russia
will not change despite whoever becomes
the US president. What's my opinion?
Absolutely correct. Won't change. Why do
I say this? It's because the US
president doesn't decide what happens.
Trump wanted friendship with Putin. What
happened?
The US president doesn't really decide
what happens. It is the deeper powers in
the US that decide what happens and that
doesn't change. So Putin was essentially
alluding to the primacy of the deep
state in the US. He has spoken about it.
Men in black suits and all that he
speaks about, doesn't he? He was talking
about the deep state. So he's absolutely
right. I completely agree with him.
Vijesh says if the leadership of India,
Russia and China falls, the country will
fall and become a US vasal. Similarly,
the US must have vulnerabilities that
could lead to the fall of its hijgemony
if exploited. The US
has a great strength. What's the
strength?
Their leadership is not visible.
Those who really rule their nation and
the empire, we don't know who they are.
That is the great strength of the US.
The president is just a puppet. The role
of the president is to divert the
world's attention from away from where
the real power resides.
That's the rule of the role of the US
president.
So if the leadership of the US falls, if
hypothetically the US president
something happens to him, the vice
president will step in. If something
happens to the vice president that the
speaker of the house or whatever the
hell it is that there's a change of
chain of command, they'll step in.
Eventually some librarian steps in. It
doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter who's the president.
The nation is taken care of by those who
actually rule it. So the US
Yeah. The vulnerabilities, we don't know
what they are. That's the great strength
of the US. The existence of the deep
state.
Prashant says, "How powerful is the ICC?
Can they arrest world leaders?" The
International Cricket Council. Z
the international cricket council can't
arrest world leaders
the international criminal court nothing
not not much
you know whenever the ICC gives a
judgment that suits the US the US can
put it put its full force behind the ICC
judgment but when the ICC says something
that doesn't suit the US the US will
oppose it the US so the ICC if it is
doing something that suits US interests
then the ICC can be reasonably powerful.
So if they have put out an arrest
warrant against some world leader and
that world leader is overflying a
country that supports the ICC that that
country can send fighter planes to to to
bring the plane down and they can arrest
the world leader they can do that. So in
that case the ICC has some power to some
extent. Yeah. Vive Singh says if India
is indeed able to explore our rare earth
and crude oil successfully do you think
the US's attitude will change towards
us? Certainly. Yeah.
Um if India rare earths Yeah. See for
rare earths we depend on China. Uh and
if we become completely self-sufficient
in rare earths which we can be if we
develop the mining u infrastructure and
all that then it will make us less
dependent on China. it won't really
affect our relationship with the US. But
yeah, the US will see that India has a
stronger hand now for sure. But if we
are able to
ex you know make a major crude oil
discovery that makes us entirely
self-sufficient in crude oil that will
be a great game changer for India. It'll
make India genuine utarchy. Right? So
it's very important that we now go full
full force in ex exploring the various
oil reserves that we probably have but
we have never bothered to do that in the
past. I I'm hearing some ministers
who have been saying for the past few
months that you know we are on the verge
of a major oil discovery similar to
whichever nation. Um so if that happens
great but let it happen and if it
happens the US's attitude will
definitely change towards India for
sure. Definitely.
MK says is deep state a boon or a bail
for the US and its people. It's both.
It's both. It's both.
Prashant says exhome minister said that
the US asked India not to react after
2611.
Okay.
Who's the ex-home minister? Is it um who
was the home minister then? Was it Mr.
Chadamaran or was it Mr. Shivraj
Chawhan?
Not sure who I think both of these
gentlemen were involved in the home
ministry
around that time. I think when 2611
happened I probably it was Mr.
not Shivaj Johan sorry Shivaj Patil
Shivaj Patil I apologize Shivaj Patil I
think he was the role minister then
eventually it was Mr.
who who took it took over the position.
I'm not exactly sure about the
chronology and I'm not sure who's the
homeist who said this but it is entirely
possible and I would not be surprised at
all if the US told India not to react
and uh and India did not did not react
initially Dr. Manm Singh had demanded
that the head of the ISI should come to
India and explain what happens and so on
and the Pakistani prime minister of the
time had actually agreed but after a few
days they walked back and they said we
are not sending any money and they
started sending dosias and and stuff
whatever and India did not take any
action against Pakistan despite this
clearly being a Pakistani terrorist
attack on India one of the most heinous
terrorist attacks against India and uh
nothing nothing was done Dr. man did not
even speak up for a few days.
Uh yeah, so that's how it went. That's
how India was back in the day. Sam
Lovely says, "The future of H1B with
$100,000 fee. Will the visa program
stay? And what happens to existing H-1B
visa holders in the US?"
Um the visa program will most likely
stay and now it's going to have this
fee, right? So the existing H1B visa
holders I don't think there's going to
be any impact for them as until they
have to renew the visa. I'm not sure how
many years it it takes before you have
to renew the visa whether it's 3 years
or 5 years or whatever but eventually
you have to renew it right. I suppose
that that's when you have to pay that
$100,000 fee if
Yeah, probably. Is it a onetime thing?
Is it a multiple time thing? every time
you renew due to due to pay 100,000 that
would make it super expensive. But I'm
sure that if the talent is good enough
then the US companies would be able to
afford that $100,000 every once in 5
years. That should not be a lot for
them. So I think it's going to come up
when the visa renewal happens and in
that case the company will be willing to
renew only if the person is genuinely
going to provide the kind of value which
makes that $100,000 in dollar investment
for 5 years a viable investment with a
positive return on investment. So many
of these H1Bs will most likely not be
renewed.
Only the top performers will be allowed
to stay. Uh so that's what will most
likely happen to existing H-1B visa
holders in the US. They are safe as long
as the visa is there. They will not be
affected right now. But when the visa
renewal happens at that time their their
future will be decided by their
companies.
Uh the visa program will most likely
stay. It will now become kind of an
elite visa. Yeah. Only the top
performers will be given H1B visas
because the companies otherwise won't
sponsor the visa. Right. That is what
happens.
Uh Dave says the new Japanese PM is a
singer. Another Zelinski installed.
It doesn't matter who's the Japanese PM.
Japan is not a sovereign nation. It
doesn't matter at all. The only prime
minister who mattered after 1945 was
Shinszu AB.
It doesn't matter who's the prime
minister. The Japanese prime
ministership is a revolving door. Every
few months, every couple of years, a new
prime minister comes and goes. Comes and
goes. It doesn't matter who it is,
whether it's a singer or a horse rider
or a gymnast or a professor or an
economist
or an athlete or an actor or whatever.
It makes no difference whatsoever. The
Japanese prime minister is not relevant
unfortunately because Japan is sadly not
a sovereign nation. It's a nation under
permanent foreign military occupation.
Akar says, "How long can the US and
India sustain the Sarif war? The US can
sustain it for the next 300 years.
The US can do it. It means the two
economies decoupled. That's it. It can
go on forever if they want." God
godliness says, "How do you see the
future of the world by60? Do you see one
power dominating all with AI and quantum
computing? Do you see a multipolar
world, one government system for all? Do
you see the remains of third world war?
Where will the world be in 20360?
What sort of world will we have in60?
I think
probabilistically
you will either have a one world order,
one world government or a bipolar world
most likely by 2016. I think the
probability is highest for this sort of
scenario. Probably not a uniolar world
order,
probably a bipolar world order by60.
Who will those two polls be is the big
question.
Will it be the US? So most likely you
will have US on one side. Who is going
to be on the other side. Is it going to
be China or is it going to be Russia or
is it going to be India or is it going
to be a coalition of these three
countries?
Because the only way you can have
someone stand up to the US and balance
the US out like the situation you had in
the 20th century. The only way this
happens
is if either China or Russia become as
powerful as the US or China, India,
Russia collaborate.
So most likely you will have some kind
of bipolar world order. That's how I see
it. One world government, one world
government system for all. I think that
is less likely and I hope there is no
third world war because there will be
nothing left after that. If if a third
world war happens.
Viraj Mahhara says trying to boy
geopolitics from first principles but
not getting an issue and no response for
support. I will look into it sir. Thank
you very much. Akar says if you if you
already have nuclearpowered submarines
then what stops us besides funds from
making a nuclearpowered aircraft
carrier.
We don't need one that's what stops us.
It's a gigantic investment.
Why do we need an aircraft carrier?
First of all, it's an obsolete platform
from the 20th century.
I don't care what so and so military
expert is saying. I have no interest in
someone's
uh authority that I have been a military
a naval officer for 70 years. That's why
I am the right authority to speak about
this. I don't I don't care.
I look at things from a logical
perspective. I have some understanding
myself my on my own. My opinion is that
the aircraft carrier is an obsolete
weapons platform. It's an obsolete
thing. The principal ship,
the principal naval ship of the 21st
century is the submarine. Nothing is
more deadly than a submarine. An
aircraft carrier is a status symbol.
It's a visible thing. If you are a
superpower with no challenge, nobody to
challenge you, then an aircraft carrier
is how you bully other nations.
But an aircraft carrier cannot survive
in a contestant contested environment
during a time of war. It will be wiped
out. It is a super enticing target. It
is a mathematical probability. It is not
a mathematical probability. It's a
mathematical certainty that it it'll be
destroyed with a sufficiently capable
adversary in front of you. It's as
simple as that. An aircraft carrier is a
gigantic waste of money.
And especially for India, we don't need
an aircraft carrier. Why? We already
have unsinkable aircraft carriers in the
sea in in the in the Bay of Bengal, the
Andaman Islands. Militarize those
islands.
Make proper air strips there. Put a
couple of hundred fighter planes there.
That's your aircraft carrier.
That gives you gigantic
sphere where you can project power in a
massive manner. In the western Indian
Ocean, the sea of Saashtra, why don't we
reclaim some land in the Lakshodi
islands and build a couple of unsinkable
aircraft carriers there? It will cost
probably less money than building these
ships.
So, we have at least one aircraft
carrier. That's good. Retain it. I'm not
saying we should scrap it. It's good
that we have it. And it it gives our our
sailors the expertise, you know, the
knowhow of how to operate these ships.
Good. But we we don't need more of these
things. Tremendous. It's a tremendous
cost. for the co for the price of one
aircraft car let's say $5 billion
you could make you could build 50
submarines that cost a hundred million
each now some geniuses will say oh but
no submarine costs $50 million $100
million submarines cost half a billion
dollars
Google the Gothand class submarine
okay so yeah so what stops us common
sense stop us stops us okay sir Ban
Chakraarti says Can market economy make
Russia global economic uh leader? Why
did they miss the computer and silicon
revolutions of the 1980s and 1990s?
1980s the Russian econ Russia was
declining.
Russia's standards had declined. Russia
had Russia was already a decade behind
the US. Even during the super
supercomput era of the 1960s and 70s,
Russia's decline started with the death
of Stalin. Their standards started
declining.
Okay.
they were more busy with their political
intri intrigues and power struggles
within Russia than in these matters. So
they were already way behind the US by
by 1980. So yeah, that's what happened.
Um and they missed these revolutions
like you say. Uh can a market economy
make Russia a global economic leader? A
market economy? Not necessarily. Is
China a market economy? China is not
really a market economy. It's a state
managed state controlled economy with
five-year planning and all that. Um it
is a capitalistic system with complete
full state control. It's not a market
economy and still they are the second
largest economy now. So I don't think a
market economy is what Russia needs.
Every nation is different. The something
that works for one nation isn't
necessarily going to work for a
different nation. So I don't think
Russia needs a market economy.
Anoj art says sad to see the EU being
Islamized cannot be re reversed. Not our
problem, not our concern. And I'm
neither sad nor happy. It's up to them.
It's their their life, their countries,
their problem. If it is a problem in
their opinion, I don't care. Top Gun
says if fiat money isn't backed by
physical commodities, what gives its
value? Is the dollar stronger because of
it is enforced on other countries?
What gives fiat money value is the
ability of the issuer of the currency to
enforce
the currency and its stat status in the
world. So let's say I I let's say I
create a new country. Okay, hypothetical
completely hypothetical thought
experiment. Let's say I create a new
country. I I I go and capture the moon
and I you know start an economy on the
moon and I start trading with earth with
earth countries. So I've declared
independence on moon. I the moon is a
separate country and I am going to issue
paper currency from the moon. It is
backed up by nothing. But because I have
the technology to conquer the moon, I
can bully all the nations on the earth
that I will conquer you all also unless
you accept my paper currency because I
have weapons that you cannot imagine,
you can you can't dream of. And I have
technology that that is beyond your
wildest dreams. So do as I say or else.
So then because I have this
my my word is backed up with this
bullying force with with with this with
my ability to unleash mayhem and and
apocalypse on the countries because I
have the ability to do that. So all the
countries will have to do what I say. So
my fiat currency which is backed up by
nothing suddenly becomes the only
currency in the world and it act
actually has value because it is backed
up by my power.
So fiat money doesn't necessarily have
to be backed up by physical commodities.
What gives it gives it value is the
ability of the issuer to enforce it by
force. That's what gives it value. Um
and that's why the US dollar has value
and it is the strongest and most
important currency in the world. that
that's the only reason why Kapay
developer says do you think China was
developed by the US in the 60s and 70s
to counter Russia land and sea curture
um China wasn't developed by the US but
China developed itself in a certain way
not in a very logical or or very capable
way as long as Maoatung was in power but
it it it came on the right track after
the death of Maoatung and the advent of
Ding Shaoping as the leader of China.
Now uh so the the Chinese developed
China but the Americans aided and
abetted the rise of China after the they
thought between the two countries which
was uh midwifed by Kissinger and Nixon.
So that's where China's fortunes start
changing and China starts implementing
the Singapore model in China in a very
different way obviously because
Singapore is this little thing and China
is massive but they they take
inspiration from from Singapore they
sent they they send bureaucrats and
whatnot to study the Singapore model.
The Singaporeans are are are happy to
teach the Chinese what they're doing to
share uh their best practices and
whatnot and the Chinese start
implementing implementing that in China
and that's where everything changes. And
obviously in 1969 the Russians wanted to
nuke China and the and the Americans
came in the way and they prevented
Russia from doing that. And that's
that's uh something that gave the
Chinese more confidence that the US you
know can be utilized as something that
uh helps us.
Yeah. So that's how it happens.
Okay. Okay. We have crossed 2 hours. So
let's please take uh please stop taking
super chats. I will end this soon but I
will obviously finish the remaining
super chats. SS Phoenix says Indians
need to move away from just ro learning
and obsession with institutions like the
British hangover. The dream of India is
of Indians becoming innovative by a
competency and inspired like Einstein
and Chandra Shikha. Indians need to move
away from this but they can't because
you have to spend 20 years stuck in an
education system that is that is still
in the in the 1800s mindset. The
education system is still completely
colonial and because every Indian Indian
citizen every Indian kid has to pass
through roughly two decades of this
horrific education system their minds
get destroyed.
That's why Indians are the way they are.
We need to move away from this. But the
only solution is to reform the education
system.
Without this this reformation of the
education system, nothing will change.
We will keep on crying even 20 30 years
down the line that Indian Indians need
to move away from road learning and all
that. But unless the government takes
the steps and implements these reforms
nothing will change and nothing is being
done. So that's where we are right now.
Pratam says reading about Shri Shri
Pandit Nuji's miracles make made my
blood evaporate. Okay.
If those decisions were reversed,
omitted, could be could we be a genuine
superpower by the 70s, right? My heart
clenches with angst.
See, in 1947,
India had the most developed
infrastructure of all the Asian nations.
India had a worldclass navy. India had a
battle tested, warested armed force.
India had the whatever the British left
behind the the the infrastructure of
occupation and extraction that we could
have built upon to create a proper
infrastructure that serves the nation.
We were not in ruins like Japan. We were
not smoldering in ashes like China. If
we had implemented
even a Russian style socialist economy,
then by 1970 we would have been a
superpower.
Yeah.
incredible opportunities lost
those 20 30 years. India should have
grown at 15% every year. The Indian
economy.
So yeah, what can I say? You're right. I
agree with you. Akar says Russia offered
to co-develop Sukoy 57 and India funded
Russia's FGFA. However, Russia then
refused to totite promising to do so.
How can India now trust Russia to not do
the same upfront to trust but verify?
Verify then trust. If they are offering
it, we need to see evidence of what
they're offering, right? So, you don't
transfer the full money.
You you have to do it in a very
step-by-step calibrated manner. You
don't blindly trust anybody, even
Russia, because we've had these
experiences with Russia, right? We spent
so much money on the on the FGFA fighter
plane co-development and they they were
creating problems. they were not um I'm
sure some of the blame was India's also
you know expecting too much from the
aircraft but u they probably were not
willing to share all the technology
which is a big problem so if they are
saying that they will co-develop the so
no it's co not co-development it's
already developed it's co-production
India will set up a production line in
India and all the technology will be
fully transferred to India that's the
promise so we will have to if we go
ahead with this we will need proper
asurances and the money needs should not
be put forward until we can see clear
evidence that the full technology is
being transferred. So you can't blindly
trust anybody, right? So it has to be
negotiated properly in a stepby-step
phase by phase manner in in such a way
that this time we don't lose money
unnecessarily without getting anything
return.
Uh and obviously now the times have
changed in 2018 Russia was not in the
kind under the kind of pressure it is
today. Russia needs India as an ally
today. And uh so yeah, we'll have to
look into it from that perspective.
SS Phoenix says Dutch and city of London
elites are the ones controlling
neoliberal and neocon polace in the
west. Ukraine is to Russia what Israel
is to Iran what Pakistan is to Barat.
Indians need to stop falling for
pro-Israel
sigh ops.
Okay. If you say so sir um once again I
am not sure what the Israeli angle could
possibly be in here. Obviously, Israel
is the unconditional ally of the US. Um,
Dutch and city of London elites are the
ones controlling neoliberal and neocon
policy in the west. Ukraine. Okay. See,
like I've said, the US does have a deep
state. No question about that.
And the this deep state may not
necessarily be limited to the geography
of the US. Maybe it's something that
spread beyond and maybe it controls way
more than the US in which case you could
have various elites who control whatever
but I am not aware of that. I have not
seen any evidence of that. If so the
deep state doesn't leave behind a
breadcrumb trail.
So uh what you're saying is definitely
possible but I can't endorse it because
I don't have evidence of that. But I I
hear you sir. That's what I can say. I
hear you. Uh Dimnor Singh says why don't
we have our own deep state or do we
does India have an extra constitutional
extra electoral center of power?
Does the Indian prime minister represent
merely a puppet or merely a figurehead
who doesn't really have power? I think
India doesn't have a deep state
and maybe there is an attempt to create
a deep state in India possibly by
outside forces which will serve outside
interests possibly. Um why don't we have
a deep state of our own that serves our
own interests because we aren't
intelligent enough to do that. We don't
play those games. We should see we we
understand the concept of a deep state.
What is the concept of a deep state in a
political party? Kingmaker
all Indian polit political official who
understand the the concept of kingmaker
that you have a person in a political
party who actually calls the shots but
that person doesn't come in the front
they appoint someone to be the chief
minister prime minister but they from
behind the scenes control everything
that's kind of a deep state situation
isn't it why don't we have it well we
have it in the at various petty low
levels but at a national level we don't
have it
buai says in the Vic period everyone
used to play pray to Lord Indra. We are
talking about geopolitics sir we will
discuss geopolitics why don't we pray to
lord Indra anymore that's not a
geopolitics question sir all right sir
we are discussing only geopolitics today
see the title of the live stream
geopolitics super chat episode we will
we will discuss geopolitics only today
aar says Dr. Kota Har Narayan chief
architect of the is against buying any
foreign jets as it would deal decisive
blow to India's AMCA. How do we then
deal with gap of squad and strength?
What should we do? I don't care what Dr.
whoever says whatever
Dr. Kota Harin Narayan the chief
architect of the he doesn't get to
decide India's defense policy right
he is an engineer
he should talk about engineering
let the government of India decide what
is best you know India's best interests
I we we thank him for being the chief
architect of the he deserves the fullest
respect from the people of India for
what he has
But he is an engineer.
I I don't think he's some kind of
geopolitical expert, right?
So I'm not sure if he should be talking
about what we should buy, what we should
not buy.
They just needs to be improved.
Right? The the variant that we have
right now, it's the first generation
variant. We need to come up with the
mark 1 A, then mark 2 and so on, which
would be further improvements. Like I've
said so many times, aircraft
engineering, aircraft design is it's all
about iterative improvements. You first
start produ producing a basic version
which is not the best version but you
start producing it and you start using
it. Then you you implement
improvements that is the second
generation fighter plane. The same they
just but they just mark 1a or whatever.
Then then you do some more changes and
make it even even better fighter plane
that becomes the mark 2. Then eventually
it becomes a world class thing at some
point. Maybe it already is. I'm not
saying it's not. But
if we buy foreign jets right now, how
does it deal a decisive blow to the
AMCA?
It gives the AMC a breathing time. It it
takes the pressure away from the AMC
AMCA program. The AMCA will not come
into production until the 2030s. What do
we do until then?
So I don't agree at all if Dr. Kot
Harinar has actually said this. I don't
if he has said this I don't agree with
it. We need numbers. We need some
interim solution
and for that we most likely should
acquire
100 200 whatever number of some other
type of fighter plane either the Rafal
or the SOA 57 or maybe both as an
interim stop gap measure. We need that
urgently.
Pratik says, Pratik Vora says, "You keep
saying Indians have low standards. How
do you see it going in the long run? Are
the West's standards decreasing day by
by the day already started with the
education system?" Yeah. West the
western
western civilization is what what they
like to call it. It is declining. You
can see the decline very clearly.
You can see the decline in so many
different ways.
In the 1990s,
listen to the music music for example
that came out from the west in the
1990s. Listen to the music that is is is
in in vogue today. Mumble rap and god
knows what other garbage and that is
what they find aesthetically pleasing
today. That the Gen Z and millennials
and all that. That's the decline in
quality and standards that you're seeing
right there.
If you look at the the living standards,
the the way of life and all the and so
much more everything all the standards
are declining education system standards
are declining especially in the US the
standards have declined drastically
education system wise in the US and I'm
not sure about the other countries in
the EU and so on. I think their
standards may be slightly higher still
but overall yeah they are making all
kinds of compromises to accommodate all
kinds of garbage. So overall it it's
going down. Everything is going down.
India,
India also you could say it's kind of
declining the standards. The more
reservations you implement, the more the
standards decline
and the more you will have people
wanting to leave the country. So overall
here, see when I say Indians have low
standards, I'm not blaming the people of
India. The system is in is is is
enforcing those these low standards,
right?
It's not the fault of the people of
India that the nation suffers from from
low standards. Indians are the victims
of this system of low standards. This
this imposition of low standards on them
and they don't even realize that this is
being done to them. That's the problem.
Okay. Dnour Singh says is a swarnabumi
hostile towards India today? No. By
swarnabumi I assume you mean Thailand.
Thailand is not hostile to India at all.
Um,
Thailand of course is you could say an
ally of the US. So that is the case but
it is not hostile towards India in any
shape or form. Not at all. Not at all.
Divor Singh says what's going on with
the pope spreading communist propaganda
and talking about climate change and
saying illeg illegal immigration is
fine. Well, I am not aware of what the
pope has been saying but uh it's the
first ever American pope, isn't he?
So well if if he is saying such things
well I would not be surprised too much
right so he's spreading communist
propaganda well that's interesting and
talking about climate change well
Americans do talk about climate change a
lot it all started with Al Gore didn't
it
what was the thing an inconvenient truth
or something the year 2000 or 2001
around that time quarter century ago Al
Gore started it all and the pope is also
saying that illegal immigration is fine
Well, okay. I wasn't aware of I've not
been kept keeping track of what the Pope
is doing, but okay. Interesting.
Interesting that he's saying that. Not
surprising though, considering the fact
that he's an American. Vamshi Khalim
says, "The Indian air chief recently
revealed that many Pakistani F-16s were
shot. India is becoming openly
confrontation with the US. Permanent
change in India's vision and policy.
India finally woken up."
Um see if if the air chief is saying
that uh a certain number of Pakistani
F-16s were destroyed it's a
confrontation with Pakistan not with the
US. India is not being confrontational
with the US. India is not that stupid.
Um India is taking a hard line with
Pakistan which we need to which is fine
and I I
seriously don't understand why are we
revealing all this now.
If we had shot down let's say seven
F-16s or nine F-16s or whatever or
destroyed half of them on the ground.
Why didn't we reveal reveal that in the
beginning itself? Why say say all this 7
months later? Oh not seven whatever
whatever it happened in May now we are
in October May to June July August
September 5 months later why
why do that I I don't get it.
So anyway my point is that we are not
being confront confrontational with the
US. Uh we are taking a very hard line
with Pakistan and that's going to be the
new policy. That's going to be the
policy going forward. We will take no
more BS from Pakistan. That's the deal.
Vive Singh says China is producing jets
at rocket pace. Russia too despite in
war is moving its defense industry at a
rapid pace. Did we miss a chance by not
spending on R&D?
We have missed many of these chances. Um
you know the Chinese have been producing
warships like in India people produce
samosas
you know
they're churning out warships like
samosas and vodap house the Chinese and
the same thing when it comes to their
fighter planes and how many fighter
planes are we producing per year like 12
16 what is it what's the number they're
sleeping
I just don't get what we are doing
Yeah. And uh now we are we have kind of
woken up about R&D. We have various
private players who are working on the
jet engine program and other things. But
India is a very reactive very lethargic
nation and uh it's it's very
disappointing overall.
Air semanticor says what about building
gouache submarines?
I am in favor of building the smallest
submarines that's possible.
by while maximizing lethality.
Why build gigantic things? Submarines
are supposed to be stealthy objects,
stealthy assets.
The larger a submarine is, the lower is
its stealth and the more uh detectable
it is.
Ideally, we should
miniaturaturize everything. Instead of
building gigantic warships,
destroyers, we should build missile
boats with long legs.
A missile boat. Don't invest more than
10 20 million on each. And each missile
boat should carry about three brahos
missiles. And we should have let's say a
100 of these these
or even 300 of these. So if if one of
these things costs $20 million and if
you have 100 that's2 billion if you have
300 it's 6 billion for the price of one
aircraft carrier you can have 300
missile boats with long legs which you
can disperse all over the Indian Ocean
region each with three Brahmos missiles.
It is a frightening prospect for any
enemy. frightening
because if you have one big warship with
128 missiles, taking one warship out
will disable those 128 missiles,
neutralize them. But if you have a swarm
of missile boats, tiny missile boats,
imagine the nightmare for the enemy. Now
transpose that to submarines.
Instead of having this big golad
submarine which costs you a billion
dollars, have 10 small submarines in its
place and disperse them all over the
place. Each of them has a nuclear
capability of whatever capability. Some
are hunter killers, some are ballistic
missile submarines. Imagine how much
more difficult it becomes for the enemy.
Think logically and rationally my dear
Indian people.
Size doesn't matter in everything.
Okay. Sometimes
the reverse is more dangerous.
All right. It's it's all about
distributed lethality. That is what
makes you dangerous. Not concentrated
lethality. Distributed lethality is what
what is really what you want. DN Singh
says what were the geopolitical
implications of the removal of the gold
standards and shift to fiat currency of
the in the US?
It was the essentially the imperial
moment. allout imperial moment of the
US. Until then, they were playing by the
rules that they had imposed upon
themselves that the US dollar we're
going to play nice. We're going to
actually have a proper value associated
with with the US dollar. So, if I have
this much currency in circulation, I'm
going to have exactly that much gold in
my vaults in Fort Knox and where
whatever else place. Yeah. But after
1971 they they unlin the US dollar from
the from the gold standard and the US
became the the dollar became a fiat
currency
and for some time they they pegged it to
the price of petroleum because they
controlled Saudi Arabia and whatnot
and Iran also at the time. Yeah. So that
was the petroleer era. Then around 79
even that was jettisoned and it became
completely
you know completely totally fiat
currency. It was you know it was
enforced through the US military muscle.
So the geopolitical implications of that
is that it it made the US a more
hegemonic more tyrannical power
eventually. Yeah. So right now why does
the US dollar still have the status of
the US of the global reserve currency?
It's it's imposed by force.
If if the BIRS nations for example were
to stop using the the US dollar, the US
will actually go to war against BIRS
nations, especially India and South
Africa, the weaker ones. So that's the
deal. It it it made it was this signal
that the US is becoming more and more
hegemonic and tyrannical. Dimn Singh
says what happens when the Arctic snow
melts and sees north of Russia and
Canada open up there's going to be a
whole new uh whole new contest over
there whole new competition Arctic
competition the Arctic uh the Arctic
trade routes and and the thing is that
you know that that region has a lot of
oil and gas reserves which which until
now have been kind of inaccessible or
very hard to access because of the the
thickness of the sheet ice that covered
these regions. But now with the melting
of the ice and all that, all of this is
opening up and Russia is going to
definitely exploit these oil and gas
reserves there. Uh the Americans will
also do that because Alaska is all the
way up there and Canada also because
Canada has a presence there. So Russia,
the US,
Canada is kind of a proxy of the US. So
Russia and the US are going to be in
competition uh for exploiting these res
these resources. China is going to be
involved because the Russians want China
to be involved in there and possibly
even India. So India, China, Russia and
the US will be involved there. The
Canadians and the Europeans also will be
involved in some shape or form. So it's
going to be a new uh region of
contention and geopolitical competition.
And obviously it's going to open up new
trade routes also. So Russia will no
longer have to uh you know it will give
Russia more options for trading with
various nations. So yeah it's
competition is going to hot up heat up
really significantly over here. Us says
US fears India's rise and as Russia and
China are declining demography. The US
doesn't fear India's rise. The US wants
to prevent
India's rise. Right now there's nothing
that the US fears about India. There is
nothing about India that frightens the
US today.
India is kind of a joke to the US today.
Okay, let's let's be very clear about
this. The US does not fear India today.
There is nothing in India that is
fearsome today. India as a nation beset
with mediocrity and low standards. And
despite these mediocrity and low
standards, India is still growing at 6.5
or whatever person per year because of
the inherent potential of the people of
India.
Okay. And even if India keeps on growing
at just 6% 6.5% per year for the next 20
years, 30 years, India will transform
into a
into eventually something that that
scares the US. So in 20 30 years time,
India could be the next China. With all
the problems, all the faults, all the
problems, India will still become the
next China in 20 30 years. That's what
the US wants to prevent.
They don't fear India. In 2030 years,
India could be fearsome. So they don't
want a fearsome India in the future.
That's why they they want to deal with
India right now. And they have all the
plans in place. And do we blame them for
that? They are doing what any power
would do, any great power, any
superpower would do. Paris is
manticores. Shouldn't we start using AI
to focus on bio research, genetic
enhancement, large batonical
engineering, pre-space travels, adaptive
enhancements, etc. to lay the foundation
of for the next great game. You see, you
should do that.
But do we have
any highquality research institutes in
the country where you have researchers
who actually are interested in doing
research? Who are India's great
researchers today? Tell me, name one
person who is a great researcher in this
country today. Name one scientist who
who
is globally internationally recognized
because he has he or she has made some
genuine contributions in their field.
Name one person today.
If we have nobody
then where will this research happen?
If we are producing no new talent or or
the or if all the good talent we are
producing wants to leave the country
then where will we do all this research?
And secondly, let's say we have
highquality researchers.
But do we have our own AI? We'll have to
use foreign AI which will I promise you
not give you the results you want. Do
you understand the problems? Do you
understand what India is lacking
strategically? Do you understand what
where we are failing?
Why aren't we taking the steps and
measures to rectify these issues? Why
aren't we creating globally worldclass
research institutes with high and
retaining highquality talent? That's
number one. Secondly, why aren't we
developing our own indigenous worldclass
AI? That's number two. What on earth is
India doing? Do you understand the
problems?
Divor Singh says,
"Will my pager or phone blast if I talk
enough about Jewish bankers?" I I would
say I would recommend don't try it.
Don't try it.
You never know, sir. You never know. You
never know. Shubam Vare says, "How is
Vav Shubam, I'm sorry, says, how is
Russia still alive as a nation? I don't
get it."
Why don't you get it?
It's because you have some
presuppositions and assumptions about
Russia. Maybe you have assume assumed
that Russia is a weak
precariously balanced little nation that
has nothing in it. Right?
The fact is that Russia is a very
powerful nation. Russia is a nation that
doesn't depend on anybody on any other
nation for anything.
It has everything it needs within its
own territory. Whether it is oil,
whether it's gas, whether it is metals,
whether it is any kind of resources,
whether it is rare earths, whether it is
uranium, whether it is whatever, whether
it it is you know the the the substances
needed for chemicals and fertilizers.
It has a high quality industrial base.
It has world-class scientists,
engineers, and it is top-ass leadership.
And it has a very powerful military and
it has the world's largest military,
world's largest nuclear arsenal, arsenal
and the means to deliver the nuclear
weapons. It has it produces it own its
own jet engines. It produces its own own
fighter planes, tanks, everything,
submarines. What does Russia lack? Why
are you surprised? I'm surprised. I'm
seriously surprised, sir. Please don't
make assumptions.
Study things properly. Research things
properly. Okay. Next, Prrenav says
Prrenav Sutbay says what are the
hindrances that we are facing developing
IMC and Chennai Vladivasto corridor.
IMC India Middle East Europe corridor.
Well, the Gulf
the moment see the IMC corridor was
announced in 2023 October or something
in New Delhi right uh during the G20
summit in New Delhi when Mr. Biden was
the president of the US and as soon as
it was announced the Hamas launched this
horrific terrorist attack on Israel
and then the Gaza war started and that
derailed the whole thing the IMAC the
Saudis wanted the beginning of the
implementation to start the the
implementation to start within 45 days
of the announcement
right so the situation in the Gulf
region is the hindrance and then you
have the Iran Israel situation as Well,
so if peace returns to the Middle East,
maybe IMC could take off, but maybe not.
Maybe the US doesn't want now today.
That's also a possibility. Chennai was
stock. How do you do that? You to go
through Chabahar, right? Chennai to I
suppose it it'll be okay. Chennai Vladi
was the eastern uh sector. So Chennai
through the straight of Malaka through
the so-called South China Sea uh through
the sea of Japan and into Vladivosto.
Okay, that's that's how I'm not sure
what is hindering that. I am not I've
not really looked into it, but I think
if you want to do it, we should go ahead
and do that as soon as possible as soon
as possible. They've not does change
come from up to down or grassroots to up
like the French Revolution. It works
both ways. It depends on the nation. It
depends on the dynamics in a nation. It
depends on the kind of structure and
setup you have in a nation and the kind
of system that you have in a nation. So
if you have let's say an authoritarian
nation let's say China typically change
comes top down the top decides
what happens what's going to happen and
then it's it's pushed downwards and it's
implemented
as per the wishes of the top that's what
happens in China in North Korea the same
thing in the US
it's a little more complex it's still an
authoritarian nation there's a lot of
top down thing but there is bottom up
also to some extent
But the bottom is allowed to vent in
various ways. But it's still more top
down than bottom up in the US. Um in a
country like India, it's it's uh there's
very little top down. It's more bottom
up in India. More bottom up. So it
depends on the context. It depends on
the nation, the culture, the system, the
the the statics and dynamics and the
political system and the societal
circumstances and so much more. Yeah.
Divor Singh says will getting powerful
give Indians civic sense or will getting
civic sense make Indians strong make
India strong making see getting powerful
will not necessarily give Indian civic
sense civic sense and hard power there's
no correlation
why does India not have civic sense
because of a lack of enforcement of the
laws do we have laws or we've got plenty
of laws
why is there no civic sense did did
Indians does not have civic sense 300
300 years ago. During the Moran era, do
you think we did not have civic sense? I
think I suspect that during the Moran
era, anybody who littered or spat on the
roads would have faced terrible
punishments.
So what brings civic sense?
If punishment is guaranteed if you break
the law, then civic sense automatically
comes in. Indians who live abroad have
the best civic sense in the world. Same
Indians. So it's because of the system
in India that we don't have civic sense.
The moment Indian start the the
government of India starts enforcing the
laws and the rules civic sense will
automatically appear magically
otherwise no matter how strong India
becomes India India will remain a
whatever Trump says. Yeah. Nubam says
will China annex Siberia or East Russia
in the future? Well if Russia allows it
to then it will happen. China would love
to do that. Will Russia allow it? As
long as Russia has strong leadership, it
won't be allowed. So, it all depends on
Russia, not on China.
Divor Singh says, "I always defend
Indians when I'm in the US in American
right-wing circles. It's getting harder
and harder. I am torn between defend
defending Indian behavior and not being
able to defend it. You don't need to
defend the in indefensible. I'm not sure
about what Indian behavior you're
talking about. Are you talking about
geopolitical behavior or are you talking
about the lack of standards in India? I
mean the lack of civic sense and the
potholes on the roads and all that
All that stuff is indefensible. You
can't defend that.
There's no point defending that. There
there's nothing to defend in that. The
lack of standards are are are a fact.
You can't defend that.
So you can only defend what is
defensible. There are things where India
is on the right side. India is right in
certain things. For example, India
versus Pakistan. I mean, India is is not
the aggressor here. India is the victim.
That's where you can defend India for
sure. But when it comes to India's low
standards and Indians doing whatever
wherever in India, littering and garbage
on the streets of whatever and potholes
and whatever else, there is nothing to
defend about that. You can't defend
that. So, yeah. All right. Let's take
one final question. Amisha says, "Thank
you, sir, for the great session. Bless
you. Thank you so much, ma'am. Thank you
so much. I really appreciate uh your
blessings. Thank you so much. Okay, I
think that brings us to the end of this
session. It's been 2 hours 41 minutes.
How did the time fly? 2 hours 41
minutes. Sorry, 41 minutes. All right,
people. Thank you so much for all your
questions. It was always always fun
taking all these questions in real time
from people from various parts of the
world. Always enjoy this. Thank you so
much everybody. And I shall now end this
live stream and I look forward to seeing
you in next week's live streams. We're
going to do this once a week the
geopolitics session because there's
always something new to discuss. So
thank you everybody. Thank you very much
once again. I really appreciate your
participation, your your your support,
your viewership and I will shall remind
you again keep learning, keep raising
keep asking questions and keep raising
your standards and I will see you in the
next one. Take care. Thank you.